<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Spur Education Blog</title>
        <link>https://spureducation.com/blog</link>
        <description>Practical K-12 staffing insights from the field.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 06:11:37 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Spur Education Blog</title>
            <url>https://spureducation.com/spur-favicon.png</url>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2026, Spur Education</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future of K-12 Staffing: Five Trends That Will Shape the Next Decade]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/future-of-k12-staffing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/future-of-k12-staffing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The staffing challenges of today are not going away. But the solutions are evolving. Here are the five trends that will define how districts staff schools over the next ten years.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you are waiting for the teacher shortage to resolve itself, you will wait a long time. The economic and cultural forces that created today&#39;s staffing challenges are structural, not cyclical. They will not reverse with a single policy change or a return to some imagined normal.</p>
<p>But that does not mean the future is bleak. It means the future belongs to districts that adapt. The staffing model that worked in 2010 does not work in 2026, and the model that works in 2026 will not work in 2035. Here are the five trends that will shape the transition.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>The future of K-12 staffing will be shaped by five trends: the rise of flexible staffing models (blending full-time teachers with part-time specialists, virtual instructors, and community experts), data-informed workforce management (using staffing data to predict needs and prevent gaps), expanded pipeline strategies (grow-your-own programs, career changer pathways, and micro-credentialing), competency-based compensation (moving beyond time-in-service salary schedules), and regional workforce collaboratives (districts sharing talent pools and resources). Districts that embrace these trends proactively will have significant staffing advantages over the coming decade.</p>
</div>

<h2>Trend 1: Flexible staffing models</h2>
<h3>The rigid model is breaking</h3>
<p>The traditional staffing model assumes every classroom has one full-time, fully certified teacher for the entire year. This model worked when teacher supply exceeded demand. It does not work when the supply is insufficient and the workforce values flexibility.</p>
<h3>What is emerging</h3>
<p>Districts are beginning to experiment with blended staffing models: a certified teacher overseeing instruction for multiple sections while paraprofessionals, specialists, and technology support individual student groups. Virtual instruction is filling gaps in subjects where qualified teachers are unavailable locally. Community experts are teaching specialized content on a part-time basis.</p>
<p>These models are not replacements for qualified teachers. They are expansions of the staffing toolkit that allow districts to put qualified instruction in front of students even when traditional single-teacher-per-classroom staffing is impossible.</p>
<h3>What to watch</h3>
<p>States are beginning to update certification policies to enable flexible staffing. Micro-credentials and specialized permits allow non-traditional educators to teach specific content areas. Districts that understand and leverage these policy changes will have staffing options that others miss.</p>
<h2>Trend 2: Data-informed workforce management</h2>
<h3>From reactive to proactive</h3>
<p>Most districts currently react to staffing problems as they arise. The next evolution is using the data districts already collect, absence patterns, fill rates, retention trends, to anticipate needs and act before problems develop.</p>
<p>The data already exists in most districts. Organizing it into dashboards and reviewing it regularly transforms staffing from a reactive scramble into a proactive operation.</p>
<h3>Smarter matching</h3>
<p>Current substitute placement systems notify every available sub about every opening. Future systems will match subs to assignments based on building familiarity, subject expertise, performance history, and teacher preferences. The right sub at the right school on the right day, not just any sub at any school.</p>
<h3>Streamlined operations</h3>
<p>Administrative tasks that currently consume hours, such as onboarding paperwork, compliance tracking, schedule management, and payroll processing, can be significantly streamlined with modern staffing platforms. This frees human capacity for the work that matters most: relationship building, coaching, and strategic planning.</p>
<h2>Trend 3: Expanded pipeline strategies</h2>
<h3>The traditional pipeline is insufficient</h3>
<p>Education program enrollment has declined significantly over the past decade. Waiting for it to rebound is not a strategy. The pipeline must be expanded to include sources that traditional recruitment does not reach.</p>
<h3>What is working</h3>
<p>Grow-your-own programs that convert paraprofessionals, substitutes, and community members into teachers. Career changer pathways that welcome professionals from other fields. High school cadet programs that cultivate interest in teaching early. Residency programs that provide on-the-job training alongside veteran teachers.</p>
<p>These expanded pipelines produce teachers who are more committed to the community and more likely to stay long-term than teachers recruited through traditional channels.</p>
<h3>The credentialing evolution</h3>
<p>States are creating new credential types: provisional certificates, micro-credentials, and specialized permits that allow qualified individuals to teach in specific contexts without a full four-year education degree. This evolution will accelerate, expanding the eligible talent pool while maintaining quality through supervision and mentoring requirements.</p>
<h2>Trend 4: Competency-based compensation</h2>
<h3>The salary schedule is losing its grip</h3>
<p>Step-and-lane salary schedules, which pay teachers based on years of experience and degree level, are the dominant compensation model in K-12. They are also increasingly disconnected from what the labor market values: skills, performance, and impact.</p>
<h3>What is emerging</h3>
<p>Some districts are experimenting with supplemental pay for high-demand skills: bilingual certification, special education expertise, STEM credentials, and leadership responsibilities. Others are offering differentiated pay for hard-to-staff schools or subjects. These approaches layer competency-based elements onto existing salary schedules without replacing them entirely.</p>
<p>The full transition to competency-based compensation will take decades and require significant labor negotiation. But the direction is clear: the most effective districts will find ways to compensate teachers based on what they bring to students, not just how long they have been in the profession.</p>
<h2>Trend 5: Regional workforce collaboratives</h2>
<h3>The competition model is losing</h3>
<p>When neighboring districts compete for the same teachers and substitutes, everyone loses. The total talent pool does not grow because districts outbid each other. It just redistributes.</p>
<h3>What is emerging</h3>
<p>Regional workforce collaboratives, where multiple districts share substitute pools, coordinate recruitment efforts, and jointly fund pipeline programs, are beginning to appear. These collaboratives expand the effective talent pool for all participating districts, reduce recruitment costs, and create shared infrastructure that no single district could afford alone.</p>
<h3>The barriers</h3>
<p>Trust, governance, and logistics are real challenges. Districts are accustomed to competing, not collaborating. But the districts that figure out regional collaboration will have access to a larger, more resilient workforce than those that continue to go it alone.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure as these trends develop</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Staffing model flexibility</strong> (what percentage of instruction is delivered by non-traditional staff?)</li>
<li><strong>Data utilization</strong> (are you using data to predict and prevent staffing gaps?)</li>
<li><strong>Pipeline breadth</strong> (how many new hires come from non-traditional pathways?)</li>
<li><strong>Compensation competitiveness</strong> (does your compensation model attract the skills you need most?)</li>
<li><strong>Regional collaboration</strong> (are you participating in shared workforce initiatives?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Assuming the old model will come back.</strong> The conditions that made traditional staffing work have changed permanently. Adapt.</li>
<li><strong>Waiting for someone else to innovate.</strong> The districts that lead on these trends will attract talent. The districts that follow will compete for what is left.</li>
<li><strong>Adopting new tools without changing processes.</strong> New tools layered onto old processes produce expensive old processes. Redesign the workflow.</li>
<li><strong>Ignoring policy changes.</strong> State certification, compensation, and staffing policies are evolving. Stay informed and leverage new flexibility as it becomes available.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Brookings Institution, &quot;The Future of the Teaching Profession&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;Reimagining the K-12 Workforce&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>Learning Policy Institute, &quot;Teacher Workforce Trends&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>National Council on Teacher Quality, &quot;Innovative Staffing Models&quot; (2024).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Ask your leadership team one question: &quot;Which of these five trends are we actively preparing for?&quot; If the answer is none, start with one. The districts that begin adapting today will be the districts that thrive in the decade ahead.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The End-of-Year Staffing Review Checklist Every District Needs]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/end-of-year-staffing-review-checklist.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/end-of-year-staffing-review-checklist.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The end of the school year is when most staffing intelligence is generated and most of it is lost. Here's how to capture it and use it to start next year stronger.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>June arrives. Teachers clean out classrooms. Contracts are signed or not renewed. Retirees say goodbye. And then summer swallows the institutional memory of what happened during the year. When August arrives, the district starts fresh with the same problems it ended with because nobody documented, analyzed, or planned based on the staffing data from the year that just ended.</p>
<p>An end-of-year staffing review takes one week of focused work and sets the direction for the next twelve months.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>A structured end-of-year staffing review captures critical data, identifies patterns, and generates a staffing action plan for the coming year. The review should cover five areas: workforce stability (who left and why), substitute program performance (fill rates, pool health, quality data), recruitment effectiveness (what worked and what did not), budget utilization (where was staffing money spent and what was the return), and pipeline development (is the future talent supply growing or shrinking). Districts that conduct annual staffing reviews and act on the findings show year-over-year improvement on key metrics. Districts that do not repeat the same problems indefinitely.</p>
</div>

<h2>The five-part review</h2>
<h3>Part 1: Workforce stability</h3>
<p><strong>What to analyze:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Total turnover number and rate (compare to prior years)</li>
<li>Turnover by building (which schools lost the most teachers?)</li>
<li>Turnover by experience level (are you losing new teachers, mid-career, or veterans?)</li>
<li>Turnover by subject area (which subjects have chronic retention problems?)</li>
<li>Exit interview themes (what reasons appear most frequently?)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Questions to answer:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Was turnover higher or lower than last year? Why?</li>
<li>Which buildings need leadership intervention based on retention patterns?</li>
<li>Are your retention strategies (mentoring, compensation, culture initiatives) producing measurable results?</li>
</ul>
<h3>Part 2: Substitute program performance</h3>
<p><strong>What to analyze:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Annual fill rate (monthly trend line)</li>
<li>Fill rate by building (which schools performed best and worst?)</li>
<li>Pool size changes (did the active pool grow or shrink?)</li>
<li>Sub performance data (average quality ratings, top and bottom performers)</li>
<li>No-show rate (trend and building distribution)</li>
<li>Cost per sub day and cost per unfilled absence</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Questions to answer:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Did fill rates improve, decline, or hold steady?</li>
<li>Is the substitute pool healthy enough for next year or does it need rebuilding?</li>
<li>What building-level interventions are needed to improve sub experiences?</li>
</ul>
<h3>Part 3: Recruitment effectiveness</h3>
<p><strong>What to analyze:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Positions posted, applications received, offers made, offers accepted</li>
<li>Time to fill by position type</li>
<li>Source of hire (which channels produced actual hires?)</li>
<li>Quality of new hires (how did this year&#39;s new teachers perform?)</li>
<li>Recruitment spending by channel (cost per hire from each source)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Questions to answer:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Which recruitment strategies produced results and which did not?</li>
<li>Where should recruitment resources be invested next year?</li>
<li>Are there positions that were chronically hard to fill? What is the plan?</li>
</ul>
<h3>Part 4: Budget utilization</h3>
<p><strong>What to analyze:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Total staffing-related spending (recruitment, substitutes, retention initiatives, technology)</li>
<li>ROI on specific investments (did the mentoring program reduce turnover? Did the pay increase improve fill rates?)</li>
<li>Cost of staffing gaps (substitute costs, coverage costs, overtime, pulled specialists)</li>
<li>Budget vs. actual for staffing line items</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Questions to answer:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Where did staffing dollars produce the most value?</li>
<li>Where was money spent with little measurable return?</li>
<li>What is the recommended staffing budget for next year?</li>
</ul>
<h3>Part 5: Pipeline development</h3>
<p><strong>What to analyze:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Student teacher placements this year (how many, and how many converted to hires?)</li>
<li>Alternative certification program participants (how many in the pipeline?)</li>
<li>Grow-your-own program status (enrollment, completion, certification progress)</li>
<li>University partnership health (are feeder programs growing or shrinking?)</li>
<li>Substitute-to-teacher conversions (how many subs became certified teachers?)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Questions to answer:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Is the talent pipeline growing or shrinking?</li>
<li>Which pipeline programs need more investment?</li>
<li>What is the projected pipeline output for the next three years?</li>
</ul>
<h2>Turning the review into a plan</h2>
<h3>Set three to five staffing goals for next year</h3>
<p>Based on the review, identify the highest-priority staffing improvements. Be specific: &quot;Improve fill rate from 78% to 85%&quot; is better than &quot;improve substitute program.&quot; &quot;Reduce first-year teacher turnover by 20%&quot; is better than &quot;improve retention.&quot;</p>
<h3>Assign ownership</h3>
<p>Each goal needs a specific person responsible for achieving it, a timeline, and a budget. Goals without ownership are wishes.</p>
<h3>Schedule quarterly check-ins</h3>
<p>Review progress on staffing goals quarterly. Do not wait until next June to discover that the plan stalled in October. Quarterly reviews create accountability and enable course corrections.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Year-over-year comparison</strong> (is each metric improving, declining, or stable?)</li>
<li><strong>Goal achievement rate</strong> (of last year&#39;s staffing goals, how many were met?)</li>
<li><strong>ROI on staffing investments</strong> (which expenditures produced measurable returns?)</li>
<li><strong>Pipeline yield</strong> (how many certified teachers will the pipeline produce in the next 1, 2, and 3 years?)</li>
<li><strong>Action plan completion</strong> (are review findings being acted on?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Not conducting a review at all.</strong> Most districts do not. This means starting every year at the same place rather than building on progress.</li>
<li><strong>Reviewing data without setting goals.</strong> Analysis without action planning is an academic exercise.</li>
<li><strong>Setting goals without assigning ownership.</strong> Unowned goals are forgotten by August.</li>
<li><strong>Losing institutional knowledge over summer.</strong> Document everything before June. The review is the institutional memory.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Education Resource Strategies, &quot;Annual Strategic Staffing Review&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>AASA, &quot;District Workforce Planning&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>AASPA, &quot;Year-End HR Review Best Practices&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Block four hours in June for a staffing review meeting. Invite your HR director, your substitute program coordinator, and one principal. Pull the data for each of the five sections above. Four hours of analysis in June prevents twelve months of repeating last year&#39;s mistakes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Run a Teacher Working Conditions Survey That Produces Real Change]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-working-conditions-survey.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-working-conditions-survey.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A well-designed working conditions survey gives teachers a voice and gives leaders actionable data. Here is how to design, administer, and act on one that improves retention.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Working conditions surveys are one of the most powerful tools a district has for understanding what teachers need to do their best work. When designed well and acted upon, they give teachers a meaningful voice and give leadership actionable intelligence. The key is following through: collecting data, sharing it transparently, and acting on the findings.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Teacher working conditions surveys are the most underused retention tool in K-12 education. When properly designed and acted upon, they identify the specific, building-level factors that drive teacher decisions to stay or leave. The critical success factors are: asking the right questions (focused on actionable conditions, not satisfaction), guaranteeing anonymity, sharing results transparently with staff, and visibly acting on at least two to three findings within 90 days. The most effective districts treat the survey as the beginning of a conversation, not the end of one.</p>
</div>

<h2>Designing the survey</h2>
<h3>Focus on conditions, not satisfaction</h3>
<p>&quot;How satisfied are you with your job?&quot; produces a number. It does not tell you what to fix. Focus questions on specific, measurable working conditions:</p>
<ul>
<li>How many hours per week do you spend on work outside of contract hours?</li>
<li>How often does your scheduled planning time get interrupted or reassigned?</li>
<li>When you send a student to the office for disciplinary support, how quickly does the administration respond?</li>
<li>How often does your principal visit your classroom for non-evaluative purposes?</li>
<li>Do you have adequate input into decisions that affect your daily work?</li>
</ul>
<p>These questions produce actionable data. &quot;Teachers spend an average of 12 hours per week on work outside contract hours&quot; is a finding you can respond to. &quot;Teachers are somewhat dissatisfied&quot; is not.</p>
<h3>Keep it short</h3>
<p>Twenty questions maximum. Survey fatigue is real, and teachers are busy. A 50-question survey will have a low completion rate, and the answers to question 45 will be less thoughtful than the answers to question 5.</p>
<p>Prioritize the ten working conditions that research most strongly links to retention: workload, autonomy, administrative support, collaboration time, professional development quality, discipline support, input in decisions, resource adequacy, class size, and recognition.</p>
<h3>Guarantee anonymity</h3>
<p>Teachers will not answer honestly if they fear their principal will see their individual responses. Use a third-party survey tool. Aggregate results at the building level only when the building has at least ten respondents. Never share individual responses with anyone.</p>
<p>Communicate the anonymity protections clearly and repeatedly. Trust takes time to build, especially in districts where past surveys were not truly anonymous.</p>
<h3>Allow open-ended responses</h3>
<p>Include two or three open-ended questions: &quot;What is the one thing that, if changed, would most improve your daily experience?&quot; and &quot;What does this district do well that should be preserved?&quot; Open-ended responses provide the narrative context that numerical scores cannot.</p>
<h2>Administering the survey</h2>
<h3>Time it right</h3>
<p>Avoid the first two weeks and last two weeks of school. Avoid the week before or after standardized testing. Early November and late February are typically good windows: teachers have settled into the year but are not yet in end-of-year survival mode.</p>
<h3>Give dedicated time</h3>
<p>Provide 15 minutes during a scheduled staff meeting for teachers to complete the survey. Completion rates for surveys sent via email hover around 40-50%. Completion rates during dedicated meeting time exceed 85%.</p>
<h3>Communicate the purpose</h3>
<p>Before administering the survey, tell teachers exactly what will happen with the results: &quot;We will share aggregate results with all staff within 30 days. We will identify two to three areas for action and share our plan within 60 days. We will report on progress within 90 days.&quot;</p>
<p>Then do exactly that.</p>
<h2>Acting on the results</h2>
<h3>Share results within 30 days</h3>
<p>Publish a summary of results, including the areas of strength and the areas of concern, to all staff. Do not sugarcoat. If 60% of teachers say administrative support is inadequate, report that number. Transparency builds trust.</p>
<h3>Identify two to three action items</h3>
<p>You cannot fix everything at once. Choose two or three findings that are actionable, impactful, and achievable within the current school year. Communicate these choices and the reasoning behind them.</p>
<h3>Report progress within 90 days</h3>
<p>Ninety days after sharing results, report on what actions were taken and what impact has been observed. &quot;Based on your feedback about planning time interruptions, we have implemented a policy that planning periods will not be reassigned except in emergencies. Since implementing this policy, planning interruptions have decreased by 40%.&quot;</p>
<p>This follow-through is the single most important step. It proves that the survey mattered.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Survey response rate</strong> (target 80%+, track year over year)</li>
<li><strong>Working conditions scores by building</strong> (identify buildings that need leadership support)</li>
<li><strong>Year-over-year trends</strong> (are conditions improving, declining, or stable?)</li>
<li><strong>Action item completion rate</strong> (did you follow through on commitments?)</li>
<li><strong>Correlation between survey scores and retention</strong> (do buildings with better scores retain more teachers?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Surveying without acting.</strong> This is worse than not surveying. It teaches teachers that their input is meaningless.</li>
<li><strong>Sharing only positive results.</strong> Cherry-picking good news destroys credibility. Share the full picture.</li>
<li><strong>Trying to fix everything at once.</strong> Two to three focused actions produce more change than ten unfocused initiatives.</li>
<li><strong>Not repeating the survey annually.</strong> A single survey is a snapshot. Annual surveys reveal trends that inform long-term strategy.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>New Teacher Center, &quot;Teaching, Empowering, Leading, and Learning (TELL) Survey&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;State of the American Teacher&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>Kraft, M. A. &amp; Papay, J. P. (2014). &quot;Can Professional Environments in Schools Promote Teacher Development?&quot; Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis.</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Ask every teacher in one building to answer one question on a notecard: &quot;What is the one change that would most improve your daily experience here?&quot; Collect the cards anonymously. Read them. If the same answer appears three or more times, you have found your highest-leverage improvement opportunity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Leadership and Culture</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Reach More Students with Your Extended Learning Program]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/extended-learning-programs-and-equity.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/extended-learning-programs-and-equity.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Your extended learning program helps the students who attend. The challenge is making sure the students who would benefit most are actually in the room.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After-school programs, summer school, tutoring, and enrichment activities are powerful tools for student growth. But the students who would benefit most are often the hardest to enroll and the hardest to retain. The gap between &quot;enrolled&quot; and &quot;consistently attending&quot; is where many programs lose their impact.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Extended learning programs often struggle to reach and retain the students who would benefit most from participation. The most common barriers are transportation (families without flexible schedules or reliable vehicles), program fees (even small amounts can deter families), information gaps (enrollment processes that do not reach all families), and scheduling conflicts (programs that do not align with family work schedules). Districts that address these barriers proactively see significantly higher participation from the students who stand to gain the most. The most effective strategies are: eliminating fees, providing transportation, conducting personalized outreach, and designing schedules around the real constraints of working families.</p>
</div>

<h2>Common barriers to participation</h2>
<h3>Transportation</h3>
<p>After-school programs that end at 5:30 PM assume a parent can pick up their child at 5:30. For a parent whose shift ends at 6:00, this is impossible. Summer programs at a central location assume the family has a car. Without reliable transportation, students simply cannot attend, regardless of how valuable the program is.</p>
<p>Provide program-specific transportation. If you cannot provide buses, partner with community organizations for carpools or offer transit passes. Survey families about transportation needs during enrollment, not after.</p>
<h3>Program fees</h3>
<p>Even modest fees can be a barrier for families on tight budgets. Fee waiver processes help but add paperwork and complexity that can discourage enrollment. The simplest approach: eliminate fees entirely and fund the program through grants, Title I funds, or district budget allocation. When the fee is zero, the barrier is zero.</p>
<h3>Information gaps</h3>
<p>Enrollment flyers sent home in backpacks reach some families. They do not reach families whose children lose papers or who are not connected to school communication channels. Effective outreach requires multiple channels: direct phone calls, text messages in the family&#39;s home language, community organization partnerships, and in-person enrollment assistance.</p>
<p>The families hardest to reach are often the families whose children would benefit most from the program. Investing extra effort to reach them is not optional. It is the purpose of the program.</p>
<h3>Scheduling conflicts</h3>
<p>A summer program that runs 8:00 AM to 12:00 PM does not work for families who need full-day coverage. An after-school program that requires a parent volunteer commitment does not work for families where both parents work. Design your program around the actual lives of the families you are trying to serve.</p>
<h2>Strategies that increase participation</h2>
<h3>1. Eliminate every financial barrier</h3>
<p>Remove fees. Provide all materials. Offer meals and snacks. Cover field trip costs. Any expense that a family must pay to participate will reduce enrollment. Budget for full access from the start.</p>
<h3>2. Provide transportation</h3>
<p>This is the single most impactful logistical investment you can make. If your program does not include transportation, many of the students who would benefit most will not attend. Budget for buses, partner for carpools, or restructure the program to use existing school-day transportation routes.</p>
<h3>3. Recruit personally, not passively</h3>
<p>Do not post a flyer and wait. Identify the specific students who would benefit most, based on academic data and teacher recommendations, and personally invite them and their families. A phone call from a trusted teacher saying &quot;I think this program would be great for Marcus&quot; is more effective than any flyer.</p>
<h3>4. Schedule around family constraints</h3>
<p>Survey families about scheduling constraints before finalizing program hours. If most parents work until 5:00, ending at 3:30 creates a gap that pushes families away. If summer schedules vary, offer flexible attendance options. Design around real constraints, not institutional convenience.</p>
<h3>5. Make the program worth attending</h3>
<p>The best enrollment strategy is a great program. When families hear from other families that their child loves the program, enrollment takes care of itself. Invest in program quality, and word-of-mouth becomes your most powerful recruitment tool.</p>
<h3>6. Track who is participating and who is not</h3>
<p>Monitor your program enrollment to understand which student populations are well-represented and which are underrepresented. If you notice gaps, investigate the barriers specific to those groups and address them directly.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enrollment conversion rate</strong> (of families contacted, what percentage enroll?)</li>
<li><strong>Consistent attendance rate</strong> (what percentage of enrolled students attend at least 75% of sessions?)</li>
<li><strong>Enrollment by outreach method</strong> (which methods produce the most enrollments?)</li>
<li><strong>Attendance trend over time</strong> (is participation stable, growing, or declining?)</li>
<li><strong>Family satisfaction</strong> (what do families say about the program experience and logistics?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Charging fees without considering the impact on enrollment.</strong> Even small fees reduce participation. Eliminate them if possible.</li>
<li><strong>Not providing transportation.</strong> This is consistently the number one logistical barrier.</li>
<li><strong>Relying on flyers and emails for outreach.</strong> Personal, direct outreach produces significantly higher enrollment than passive methods.</li>
<li><strong>Designing the schedule around staff convenience rather than family needs.</strong> The program exists for families. Design it accordingly.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Afterschool Alliance, &quot;America After 3PM&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;Extended Learning Program Participation&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>National Summer Learning Association, &quot;Increasing Program Access&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Compare your program enrollment to your school&#39;s overall student population. Are there groups of students who are underrepresented? If so, call five families from that group and ask: &quot;What would make it easier for your child to participate?&quot; Their answers will tell you exactly what barriers to address.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Gary Henderson</author>
            <category>Extended Learning</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Recruiting Career Changers into Teaching: A Practical Guide]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/recruiting-teachers-from-other-careers.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/recruiting-teachers-from-other-careers.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Career changers are the largest untapped talent pool for teaching. Here is how to design a recruitment and onboarding process that welcomes them.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A 35-year-old engineer wants to become a math teacher. She has 12 years of professional experience, a master&#39;s degree, and a genuine passion for education. She visits your district website. The careers page lists a teaching position requiring a state certification she does not have, three professional references from education settings she has never worked in, and a salary schedule that starts her at year one despite her decade of experience.</p>
<p>She closes the tab and applies to the charter school that posted on LinkedIn last week with a message that said: &quot;Career changers welcome. We will help you get certified.&quot;</p>
<p>This scenario plays out thousands of times per year across the country. The talent is available. Districts are just not designed to capture it.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Career changers represent a significant potential talent pool for teaching, particularly in shortage subject areas like math, science, and career and technical education. Research shows that career changers who receive adequate support perform comparably to traditionally certified teachers by their second year and bring real-world experience that enhances instruction. The barriers to recruiting career changers are primarily structural: certification requirements, salary schedule inflexibility, and onboarding processes designed for 22-year-olds fresh from education programs. Districts that actively recruit career changers with streamlined pathways, credit for prior experience, and mentoring support see 15-25% of new hires come from non-traditional backgrounds.</p>
</div>

<h2>Why career changers make good teachers</h2>
<h3>Subject matter expertise</h3>
<p>An engineer teaching physics brings authentic expertise that a traditionally certified teacher with a generalist science degree may lack. A journalist teaching English brings professional writing experience. A nurse teaching health science brings clinical knowledge. This expertise enriches instruction and gives students real-world context for what they are learning.</p>
<h3>Professional maturity</h3>
<p>Career changers have navigated workplace dynamics, managed projects, communicated with stakeholders, and solved complex problems. These skills transfer directly to classroom management, parent communication, and collaboration with colleagues. The professional maturity gap between a 35-year-old career changer and a 22-year-old new graduate is significant.</p>
<h3>Breadth of perspective</h3>
<p>A teaching profession composed entirely of people who went from school to college to teacher prep to school has a limited range of experience. Career changers bring perspectives from industry, healthcare, military, business, and the arts. This breadth of experience enriches the school community.</p>
<h2>How to recruit career changers</h2>
<h3>1. Partner with alternative certification programs</h3>
<p>Alternative certification programs (Teach for America, state-specific programs, university-based alternative routes) are designed for career changers. Partner with these programs to become a preferred placement district. Offer to host candidates and provide building-level mentoring.</p>
<h3>2. Market on professional platforms</h3>
<p>Career changers are not looking at education job boards. They are on LinkedIn, Indeed, and industry-specific job sites. Post teaching positions on these platforms with messaging that speaks to career changers: &quot;Bring your expertise to the classroom. We provide the certification pathway.&quot;</p>
<h3>3. Credit prior experience on the salary schedule</h3>
<p>A career changer with 10 years of professional experience who is placed at Step 1 of the salary schedule takes a devastating pay cut. Districts that allow credit for relevant professional experience (even partial credit, such as one year of salary credit for every two years of professional experience) attract significantly more career changers.</p>
<p>This requires board approval and may face union negotiation. It is worth pursuing. A career changer placed at Step 5 instead of Step 1 costs more in year one but is far more likely to stay and contribute long-term.</p>
<h3>4. Streamline the onboarding</h3>
<p>Career changers are accustomed to professional onboarding: efficient, digital, and respectful of their time. If your onboarding requires four in-person visits to central office, paper forms, and a six-week wait for a badge, you are losing career changers to employers who move faster.</p>
<h3>5. Provide intensive first-year support</h3>
<p>Career changers have professional skills but limited pedagogical training. Their first year needs: a skilled mentor, frequent classroom observation and feedback, a reduced course load if possible, and professional development focused on instructional practice rather than content knowledge.</p>
<p>The districts that retain career changers invest heavily in their first year. The districts that lose them throw them into a full teaching load with no additional support and wonder why they leave.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Career changer applications</strong> (are you attracting non-traditional candidates?)</li>
<li><strong>Career changer hire rate</strong> (of career changer applicants, how many are hired?)</li>
<li><strong>First-year retention of career changers</strong> (compared to traditionally certified new hires)</li>
<li><strong>Student outcomes in career changer classrooms</strong> (compared to similar classrooms by year two)</li>
<li><strong>Time from application to classroom</strong> (is the process fast enough for candidates with other options?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Posting only on education job boards.</strong> Career changers are not on education job boards. Go where they are.</li>
<li><strong>Starting career changers at Step 1.</strong> A $40,000 starting salary for someone earning $80,000 is a non-starter. Credit prior experience.</li>
<li><strong>Expecting career changers to navigate certification alone.</strong> Partner with alternative certification programs and guide candidates through the process.</li>
<li><strong>Providing no additional first-year support.</strong> Career changers need more mentoring, not less, because their gaps are in pedagogy, not professionalism.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>TNTP, &quot;Greenhouse Schools: How Schools Can Build Cultures Where Teachers and Students Thrive&quot; (2014).</li>
<li>National Center for Alternative Certification, &quot;Alternative Teacher Certification&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>U.S. Department of Education, &quot;Non-Traditional Routes to Teaching&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Post one of your hard-to-fill positions on LinkedIn with this language: &quot;Career changers welcome. We value your professional experience and will support your path to certification.&quot; See who applies. You may be surprised.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Rob Magliano</author>
            <category>Teacher Recruitment</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 10 Staffing Metrics Every School District Should Track]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/staffing-metrics-every-district-should-track.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/staffing-metrics-every-district-should-track.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Most districts track vacancies. That is one metric out of ten that matter. Here is the complete staffing scorecard that gives you full visibility into your workforce health.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ask most HR directors how many vacancies they have. They can tell you immediately. Ask them their pool activation rate, their cost per unfilled absence, or their offer acceptance rate, and you get silence. This is not a criticism of HR directors. It is a symptom of districts measuring the most visible metric while ignoring the most actionable ones.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>A complete district staffing scorecard includes ten metrics across four categories: workforce stability (retention rate, vacancy rate, time to fill), substitute program health (fill rate, pool activation rate, sub performance score), recruitment effectiveness (applicants per opening, offer acceptance rate, source of hire), and cost efficiency (cost per hire, cost per unfilled absence). Tracking these ten metrics monthly provides complete visibility into staffing health and enables proactive management. Most districts track two or three. The districts that track all ten make consistently better staffing decisions.</p>
</div>

<h2>The ten metrics</h2>
<h3>Workforce stability</h3>
<p><strong>1. Teacher retention rate.</strong> The percentage of teachers who return from one year to the next. Track this by building, subject area, and years of experience. The overall number hides critical variation. A 90% district retention rate can include a building at 70% that needs urgent attention.</p>
<p><strong>2. Vacancy rate.</strong> The number of unfilled teaching positions as a percentage of total positions. Track this at three points: August 1 (pre-year), October 1 (after the year starts), and January 1 (mid-year). Vacancies that persist past October indicate structural recruitment problems.</p>
<p><strong>3. Time to fill.</strong> The average number of days from when a position is posted to when an offer is accepted. This measures your hiring speed. In competitive labor markets, time to fill is a critical competitive metric. Every extra week costs you candidates.</p>
<h3>Substitute program health</h3>
<p><strong>4. Fill rate.</strong> The percentage of teacher absences covered by a substitute. Track this daily and report it weekly. Break it down by building, day of week, and time of request. The aggregate fill rate is useful. The building-specific and time-specific data is actionable.</p>
<p><strong>5. Pool activation rate.</strong> The percentage of rostered subs who accepted at least one assignment in the last 30 days. This is the gap between your paper pool and your real pool. Most districts find 40-60% of their rostered subs are functionally inactive.</p>
<p><strong>6. Sub performance score.</strong> The average post-assignment rating for your substitute pool, aggregated from teacher feedback. This tells you whether your subs are maintaining classroom quality. A declining average performance score is an early warning.</p>
<h3>Recruitment effectiveness</h3>
<p><strong>7. Applicants per opening.</strong> The number of applications received for each posted position. Track this by subject area and building. Positions that consistently attract fewer than three applicants need targeted recruitment strategies beyond standard job postings.</p>
<p><strong>8. Offer acceptance rate.</strong> The percentage of employment offers that are accepted. A low acceptance rate means you are attracting candidates but losing them at the decision point. This often indicates a compensation or working conditions gap that becomes apparent during the interview process.</p>
<p><strong>9. Source of hire.</strong> Which recruitment channels produce your actual hires? Job boards, university partnerships, referrals, internal pipelines, or other sources? This data tells you where to invest recruitment resources and where to reduce spending.</p>
<h3>Cost efficiency</h3>
<p><strong>10. Cost per unfilled absence.</strong> When a classroom goes uncovered, what does it actually cost? Include: pulled instructional coaches (their hourly rate), lost teacher prep periods (opportunity cost), combined classroom inefficiency, and administrative time spent managing coverage. This number makes the business case for investing in fill rate improvements.</p>
<h2>Building the scorecard</h2>
<h3>Start with what you have</h3>
<p>Most of these metrics can be calculated from data you already collect. Absence management systems generate fill rate data. HRIS systems have vacancy and turnover data. The work is not generating new data. It is pulling existing data together into a single view.</p>
<h3>Update monthly</h3>
<p>Weekly updates for fill rate and absence data. Monthly updates for all ten metrics. Quarterly deep-dive analysis that examines trends and triggers action.</p>
<h3>Share widely</h3>
<p>The scorecard should not live in HR. Share it with the superintendent, principals, and the school board (in appropriate summary form). When staffing data is as visible as academic data, staffing receives the same level of strategic attention.</p>
<h3>Set targets</h3>
<p>Each metric should have a target. Fill rate: 90%. Retention rate: 90%. Time to fill: 30 days. Targets create accountability and provide a clear benchmark for evaluating whether strategies are working.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>The complete scorecard</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Teacher retention rate</strong> (target: 90%+, by building and subject area)</li>
<li><strong>Vacancy rate</strong> (target: below 3% by October 1)</li>
<li><strong>Time to fill</strong> (target: under 30 days)</li>
<li><strong>Fill rate</strong> (target: 85-90%, by building and day of week)</li>
<li><strong>Pool activation rate</strong> (target: 50%+)</li>
<li><strong>Sub performance score</strong> (target: above 2.5 on a 3-point scale)</li>
<li><strong>Applicants per opening</strong> (target: 5+ for every position)</li>
<li><strong>Offer acceptance rate</strong> (target: 80%+)</li>
<li><strong>Source of hire</strong> (no target; informational for resource allocation)</li>
<li><strong>Cost per unfilled absence</strong> (calculate once, use to build ROI cases)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tracking only vacancies.</strong> Vacancies are a lagging indicator. Fill rate, retention, and pipeline metrics are leading indicators. Track both.</li>
<li><strong>Reporting data without targets.</strong> &quot;Our fill rate is 78%&quot; means nothing without context. &quot;Our fill rate is 78% against an 90% target, down from 82% last quarter&quot; is actionable.</li>
<li><strong>Not breaking down by building.</strong> District averages hide building crises. Every metric should be viewable at the building level.</li>
<li><strong>Reviewing annually instead of monthly.</strong> Staffing problems develop in weeks. Annual reviews arrive too late to prevent damage.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Education Resource Strategies, &quot;Strategic Staffing Analytics&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>AASPA, &quot;HR Metrics for School Districts&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>Frontline Education, &quot;The State of K-12 Staffing Data&quot; (2024).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Calculate three numbers: your current fill rate, your current teacher retention rate, and your pool activation rate. Write them on a sticky note and put it on your monitor. Those three numbers are the foundation of your staffing scorecard. Next week, add two more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building a Community Among Your Substitute Teachers]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/building-substitute-teacher-community.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/building-substitute-teacher-community.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Substitutes are the most isolated workforce in education. Building community among them improves retention, quality, and job satisfaction with minimal investment.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A substitute teacher&#39;s typical day: arrive at an unfamiliar school, receive minimal orientation, teach students they have never met, eat lunch alone, leave without speaking to another professional. Repeat at a different school tomorrow. This isolation is the defining feature of substitute work, and it is the primary reason subs disengage.</p>
<p>Nobody quits a community. People quit jobs. If you want your subs to stay, give them something more than a job.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Substitute teachers who feel connected to a professional community are significantly more likely to remain active in a district&#39;s pool. Community-building strategies include: regular gatherings (quarterly in-person events), digital communication channels (group text, app, or social media group), peer mentoring programs, professional development opportunities, and recognition systems. Districts that invest in substitute community report 20-30% lower sub attrition rates and higher assignment acceptance rates. The investment required is modest: most community-building activities cost less than $2,000 per year.</p>
</div>

<h2>Why community matters for substitutes</h2>
<h3>Isolation drives attrition</h3>
<p>A sub who works three days per week in three different buildings has no consistent colleagues, no break room conversations, and no professional relationships. They exist in a professional vacuum. When the work gets hard, which it always does, there is no social network to provide support, encouragement, or a reason to keep going.</p>
<h3>Community creates accountability</h3>
<p>Subs who know each other feel accountable to the group. Accepting an assignment and not showing up is easier when you are anonymous. It is harder when your colleagues will notice.</p>
<h3>Belonging increases quality</h3>
<p>Subs who feel they belong to a professional community take more pride in their work. They prepare more thoroughly. They manage classrooms more effectively. They leave better notes. They treat the work as a profession, not a gig, because the community reinforces that identity.</p>
<h2>How to build substitute community</h2>
<h3>1. Host quarterly gatherings</h3>
<p>Four times per year, bring your substitutes together. Serve breakfast or lunch. Provide a brief professional development session on a practical topic: classroom management tip, curriculum update, or technology tool. Leave time for subs to meet each other, share experiences, and build relationships.</p>
<p>Attendance at these events will start small. That is fine. The subs who attend become your core community. They recruit others. Over two or three gatherings, attendance grows.</p>
<h3>2. Create a digital communication channel</h3>
<p>Set up a group text thread, a Slack channel, or a private Facebook group for your subs. Use it to share: assignment opportunities, tips and resources, recognition of good work, and program updates. Encourage subs to post questions and share experiences.</p>
<p>The digital channel keeps the community alive between in-person gatherings. A sub who is frustrated after a tough day can vent to colleagues who understand. A sub who is new can ask for advice. This peer support costs nothing and prevents the isolation that drives people out.</p>
<h3>3. Pair new subs with veteran subs</h3>
<p>When a new sub completes onboarding, connect them with an experienced sub who volunteers as a mentor. The mentor answers questions, shares tips about specific buildings, and provides the human connection that formal onboarding cannot.</p>
<p>This mentoring relationship does not need to be elaborate. A text exchange and an occasional coffee meeting is sufficient. The new sub has someone to call when things go wrong. The veteran sub has a leadership role that deepens their commitment.</p>
<h3>4. Recognize subs publicly and specifically</h3>
<p>Monthly recognition in your communication channel costs nothing. &quot;Shout-out to Maria who received perfect ratings at three different buildings this month.&quot; &quot;Thank you to James for taking six assignments during our peak week.&quot; Public, specific recognition makes subs feel seen.</p>
<p>Extend recognition to district-level events. Invite top subs to the annual staff appreciation event. Feature a &quot;Substitute of the Quarter&quot; in the district newsletter. These gestures take minutes and communicate volumes.</p>
<h3>5. Include subs in professional identity</h3>
<p>Give subs a title that conveys professionalism. &quot;Guest Teacher&quot; carries more dignity than &quot;sub.&quot; Provide professional name badges. Include subs in relevant district communications about educational initiatives. These signals communicate that subs are part of the educational team, not temporary labor.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Event attendance rate</strong> (trending up indicates community growth)</li>
<li><strong>Digital channel engagement</strong> (messages, questions, and responses per week)</li>
<li><strong>Sub attrition rate before and after community investment</strong> (the key outcome metric)</li>
<li><strong>Assignment acceptance rate</strong> (subs who feel connected accept more frequently)</li>
<li><strong>Mentor match retention</strong> (do mentored new subs stay active longer than unmentored ones?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hosting one event and giving up when attendance is low.</strong> Community takes time to build. Commit to quarterly events for a full year before evaluating.</li>
<li><strong>Making gatherings purely administrative.</strong> If the quarterly event is just announcements and policy reviews, subs will stop attending. Mix professional development with social time.</li>
<li><strong>Not moderating the digital channel.</strong> A group chat that becomes a complaint forum erodes morale. Set norms and moderate actively.</li>
<li><strong>Treating community-building as optional.</strong> In a labor market where subs have choices, community is a competitive advantage, not a nice-to-have.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Kelly Education, &quot;Substitute Teacher Engagement&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>Frontline Education, &quot;Building Substitute Community&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>AASPA, &quot;Substitute Workforce Engagement Strategies&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Send a group message to every active sub in your district: &quot;We are hosting a breakfast for our substitute teachers on [date]. We want to meet you, hear from you, and invest in your success.&quot; Then follow through. That first gathering is the seed of a community.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Rob Magliano</author>
            <category>Substitute Teaching</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Hidden Connection Between Staffing and Student Attendance]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/attendance-and-staffing-connection.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/attendance-and-staffing-connection.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[When classrooms are unstaffed, students disengage. When students are absent, staffing becomes harder. Here's how to break the cycle.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a connection between staffing stability and student attendance that most districts do not recognize. When a teacher is absent and no qualified substitute is available, the classroom experience degrades. Classes are combined. Aides cover instruction. Students sit with worksheets. When this happens frequently, students learn that some school days are not worth attending. The staffing problem becomes an attendance problem.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Research shows a measurable correlation between teacher absence rates (and substitute fill rates) and student attendance at the school level. Schools with higher teacher absence rates and lower fill rates experience 2-5 percentage points higher student absenteeism. The mechanism is straightforward: when classrooms frequently lack qualified instruction, the value proposition of attending school weakens, particularly for students who are already on the margin of disengagement. Districts that improve staffing stability, specifically fill rates and substitute quality, often see collateral improvements in student attendance.</p>
</div>

<h2>How staffing instability drives student absence</h2>
<h3>The &quot;why bother&quot; effect</h3>
<p>When a student arrives at school and discovers their teacher is absent and a substitute is showing a movie, they internalize a message: today does not matter. If this happens occasionally, the impact is minimal. If it happens weekly, the student begins to calculate which days are worth attending.</p>
<p>This effect is strongest for older students who have more autonomy over their attendance decisions and for students who are already ambivalent about school.</p>
<h3>The relationship disruption</h3>
<p>Students attend school partly because of relationships with their teachers. When a teacher is frequently absent, that relationship weakens. When a substitute who does not know the students covers the class, the relational incentive to attend disappears for that period. For students whose primary connection to school is one specific teacher, that teacher&#39;s absence can trigger the student&#39;s absence.</p>
<h3>The quality erosion</h3>
<p>Chronic teacher absences, even when covered by substitutes, erode instructional quality. Students fall behind. Falling behind makes school frustrating. Frustration makes attendance feel pointless. The student who stops attending in November often started disengaging in September when their classroom lost instructional continuity.</p>
<h3>The signal to families</h3>
<p>When a school frequently sends students home due to lack of coverage, or when parents hear from their children that &quot;we just had a sub again,&quot; family confidence in the school erodes. Parents who lose confidence in the educational experience are less motivated to fight the morning battle of getting a reluctant child to school.</p>
<h2>Breaking the cycle</h2>
<h3>Improve fill rates first</h3>
<p>The most direct intervention is ensuring that when a teacher is absent, a qualified substitute is in the classroom. A fill rate improvement of 10 percentage points reduces the number of degraded classroom experiences proportionally. This is the staffing-side fix.</p>
<h3>Improve substitute quality second</h3>
<p>A filled classroom with a poor substitute is better than an unfilled one but not by much. When students know that sub days mean productive instruction, the &quot;why bother&quot; effect diminishes. Invest in substitute quality alongside fill rate improvements.</p>
<h3>Support teacher attendance third</h3>
<p>Invest in teacher well-being through wellness programs, manageable workloads, mental health support, and a culture where taking a necessary day off does not mean returning to chaos. When teachers feel supported, continuity improves and student engagement strengthens.</p>
<h3>Track the correlation in your data</h3>
<p>Most districts track teacher absence, fill rate, and student attendance in separate systems with no cross-analysis. Link these datasets. Do schools with lower fill rates have lower student attendance? Do weeks with more teacher absences see more student absences? The correlation in your own data makes the case for investment in staffing as an attendance strategy.</p>
<h3>Communicate with families</h3>
<p>When staffing challenges affect the classroom experience, proactive communication with families maintains trust. &quot;We had a staffing challenge today. Here is how we addressed it. Here is what your child&#39;s class worked on.&quot; This transparency is far better than a child coming home saying &quot;we did nothing today.&quot;</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Teacher absence rate by building</strong> (correlated with student attendance by building)</li>
<li><strong>Fill rate by building</strong> (correlated with student attendance by building)</li>
<li><strong>Student attendance on sub days vs. teacher-present days</strong> (is there a measurable difference?)</li>
<li><strong>Classroom coverage quality</strong> (are sub days productive or just covered?)</li>
<li><strong>Family satisfaction with classroom coverage</strong> (do parents trust the sub experience?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Treating staffing and attendance as separate issues.</strong> They are connected. Cross-functional teams should address both.</li>
<li><strong>Not analyzing the correlation in your own data.</strong> National research is persuasive. Your own data is compelling. Link your datasets.</li>
<li><strong>Accepting low fill rates as normal.</strong> Every unfilled classroom is a small push toward student disengagement. Do not normalize it.</li>
<li><strong>Ignoring the student perspective.</strong> Ask students: &quot;What is school like when your teacher is absent?&quot; Their answers will reveal the attendance connection clearly.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Clotfelter, C. T., et al. (2009). &quot;Are Teacher Absences Worth Worrying About?&quot; Education Finance and Policy.</li>
<li>Miller, R. T., et al. (2008). &quot;Do Teacher Absences Impact Student Achievement?&quot; Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis.</li>
<li>Attendance Works, &quot;School-Level Factors in Chronic Absenteeism&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Pull your school-level data for teacher absence rate, substitute fill rate, and student chronic absenteeism rate. Plot all three on a single chart by building. If the buildings with the worst staffing metrics also have the worst student attendance, you have found a lever that most districts overlook.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Gary Henderson</author>
            <category>Attendance Recovery</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Retain Teachers During Budget Cuts]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-retention-during-budget-cuts.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-retention-during-budget-cuts.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Budget cuts are coming. Teacher layoffs feel inevitable. But districts that manage cuts strategically can protect their best teachers and preserve institutional knowledge.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The budget memo arrives: a 5% reduction across all departments. The immediate instinct is to cut positions, starting with the newest hires. This approach is legally safe, politically defensible, and strategically disastrous. Last-in-first-out layoffs often remove your most energetic and most recently invested-in teachers while retaining the most expensive ones.</p>
<p>Budget cuts are real constraints. But they are not an excuse to abandon retention strategy. In fact, budget cuts are exactly when retention strategy matters most.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Districts facing budget cuts can protect retention through strategic workforce planning: analyzing which positions, not just which people, to reduce; leveraging natural attrition rather than forced layoffs; redeploying staff rather than eliminating them; and investing in the low-cost retention strategies that matter most during uncertainty (communication, recognition, and administrative support). Districts that communicate early and honestly with staff during budget uncertainty experience 30-40% less voluntary turnover than districts that remain silent until decisions are finalized.</p>
</div>

<h2>Strategies for retaining teachers through cuts</h2>
<h3>1. Use natural attrition first</h3>
<p>Every year, a percentage of your staff leaves voluntarily: retirements, relocations, career changes. If you know the budget cut is coming, freeze hiring immediately for non-critical positions. Let natural attrition absorb as much of the reduction as possible before touching existing staff.</p>
<p>Model the numbers. If your annual attrition rate is 12% and you need a 5% reduction, natural attrition may cover the entire cut if you manage hiring carefully.</p>
<h3>2. Communicate early and honestly</h3>
<p>The worst thing you can do during budget uncertainty is go silent. In the absence of information, teachers assume the worst. Rumors spread. Morale drops. Your best teachers, the ones with the most options, start looking for jobs elsewhere.</p>
<p>Communicate what you know as soon as you know it. &quot;We are facing a potential 5% budget reduction. Here is what that means. Here is what we do not know yet. Here is when we will know more.&quot; Transparency does not eliminate anxiety, but it prevents the corrosive distrust that drives voluntary departures.</p>
<h3>3. Protect high-impact positions</h3>
<p>Not all positions contribute equally to student outcomes. Before making cuts, analyze which positions have the highest impact: classroom teachers in tested subjects, special education staff, counselors with full caseloads. Protect these positions and look for reductions in areas with lower direct impact on instruction.</p>
<p>This requires courage. Cutting a coordinator position or combining administrative roles is politically harder than cutting a first-year teacher. But it protects the instructional core.</p>
<h3>4. Redeploy rather than eliminate</h3>
<p>A teacher whose specific position is eliminated may be qualified for another role in the district. Before issuing a layoff notice, explore redeployment: can they fill a vacancy in another building? Can they take a different subject area? Can they move into a support role temporarily?</p>
<p>Redeployment preserves institutional knowledge and signals to the remaining staff that the district values its people.</p>
<h3>5. Double down on free retention strategies</h3>
<p>The most powerful retention strategies cost nothing:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Visibility:</strong> Principals spending more time in classrooms and hallways during uncertain periods</li>
<li><strong>Gratitude:</strong> Specific, genuine recognition of teachers&#39; work</li>
<li><strong>Listening:</strong> Town halls, department meetings, and one-on-one conversations where teachers express concerns and feel heard</li>
<li><strong>Stability:</strong> Minimizing additional changes during the budget cycle; do not pile new initiatives onto budget cuts</li>
</ul>
<p>Teachers do not leave during budget cuts because of the budget cuts. They leave because the budget cuts reveal or worsen existing culture problems. Districts with strong cultures retain teachers through uncertainty. Districts with weak cultures see cuts trigger an exodus.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voluntary turnover rate during and after budget cuts</strong> (compare to pre-cut baseline)</li>
<li><strong>Offer acceptance rate for remaining positions</strong> (are you still attracting new talent?)</li>
<li><strong>Teacher morale survey</strong> (pulse surveys during budget uncertainty)</li>
<li><strong>Natural attrition rate</strong> (is it sufficient to absorb planned reductions?)</li>
<li><strong>Recruitment pipeline health</strong> (even during cuts, monitor your pipeline for future needs)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Going silent until decisions are final.</strong> Silence breeds fear and flight. Communicate early and often.</li>
<li><strong>Defaulting to last-in-first-out without analysis.</strong> Seniority-based cuts are legally easy and strategically costly. Explore alternatives.</li>
<li><strong>Cutting professional development and mentorship first.</strong> These are the cheapest retention tools you have. Cutting them during instability accelerates voluntary departures.</li>
<li><strong>Treating budget cuts as a one-time event.</strong> Budget pressures are cyclical. Build a workforce planning function that anticipates cuts and adjusts proactively rather than reactively.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Education Resource Strategies, &quot;Strategic Staffing During Budget Constraints&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;Teacher Retention During Fiscal Stress&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>National Council on Teacher Quality, &quot;Layoff Policies&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Calculate your district&#39;s annual natural attrition rate for the last three years. Average it. Compare that number to the reduction required by your current or anticipated budget cut. If natural attrition can cover half or more of the reduction, you have a path that does not require layoffs. Share that math with your leadership team.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Teacher Retention</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Technology Stack Every Substitute Program Needs in 2026]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/substitute-teacher-technology-tools.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/substitute-teacher-technology-tools.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[From absence management to performance tracking, here are the technology tools that transform substitute programs from chaotic to strategic.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I visit districts where the sub coordinator manages 150 substitutes with a spreadsheet, a phone, and a prayer. I visit other districts where the coordinator manages 400 subs with a modern platform and has time left over for strategic work. The difference is not the coordinator&#39;s skill. It is the tools.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>An effective substitute program technology stack includes four components: an absence management system (notifications, assignment matching, and scheduling), a communication platform (mass messaging to the sub pool), a performance tracking system (feedback collection and scoring), and a data dashboard (real-time visibility into fill rates, pool health, and trends). Most districts have the first component but lack the other three. The investment in a complete stack typically costs $3-8 per student annually and generates returns through higher fill rates, lower administrative costs, and better data-driven decision making.</p>
</div>

<h2>The four components</h2>
<h3>1. Absence management system</h3>
<p>This is the core platform. When a teacher reports an absence, the system notifies available substitutes, manages the assignment process, and confirms coverage. Modern systems use text, email, app notifications, and phone calls to reach subs through their preferred channel.</p>
<p><strong>What to look for:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Multi-channel notification (text, app, email, phone)</li>
<li>Mobile-friendly interface for subs</li>
<li>Preference management (building preferences, day preferences, sub exclusions)</li>
<li>Calendar integration for teachers reporting absences</li>
<li>Real-time status visibility for building administrators</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What to avoid:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Systems that rely solely on phone calls (lowest response rate)</li>
<li>Platforms without mobile capability (subs live on their phones)</li>
<li>Systems that cannot integrate with your HRIS or payroll</li>
</ul>
<h3>2. Communication platform</h3>
<p>Beyond individual assignment notifications, you need a way to communicate with your entire sub pool. Announcements about training opportunities, policy changes, incentive programs, and appreciation messages maintain engagement and build community.</p>
<p>This can be as simple as a mass texting service or as integrated as a feature within your absence management platform. The key requirement: the ability to segment messages (send to all subs, to preferred subs only, to inactive subs, to subs who work at specific buildings).</p>
<h3>3. Performance tracking</h3>
<p>Every substitute assignment should generate a brief feedback loop. The returning teacher rates the sub on two or three dimensions. These ratings accumulate over time to create a performance profile for each sub.</p>
<p><strong>Minimum viable system:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Post-assignment survey sent to the returning teacher</li>
<li>Three questions maximum (classroom management, plan execution, professionalism)</li>
<li>Aggregated scores visible to program administrators</li>
<li>Ability to flag subs for coaching or recognition based on scores</li>
</ul>
<p>This can be built in a Google Form connected to a spreadsheet. It does not need to be expensive. It needs to be consistent.</p>
<h3>4. Data dashboard</h3>
<p>Fill rates, pool utilization, absence trends, and performance distributions should be visible at a glance. A weekly dashboard that takes five minutes to review transforms how you manage your program.</p>
<p><strong>Essential dashboard metrics:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Daily and weekly fill rate</li>
<li>Active pool size (subs who worked in the last 30 days)</li>
<li>Fill rate by building</li>
<li>Average performance score</li>
<li>Upcoming predicted high-absence days (based on historical patterns)</li>
</ul>
<h3>Putting it together</h3>
<p>The ideal state is a single integrated platform that handles all four components. Several vendors offer comprehensive solutions. If budget constraints prevent a full-platform investment, you can build a functional stack with lower-cost tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>Absence management: Your existing platform or a dedicated system</li>
<li>Communication: A mass texting service ($50-100/month)</li>
<li>Performance tracking: Google Forms plus Google Sheets</li>
<li>Dashboard: Google Sheets or a free dashboard tool pulling from your data sources</li>
</ul>
<p>The integrated platform is better. The assembled stack is better than nothing. Do not let perfect be the enemy of good.</p>
<h2>Implementation priorities</h2>
<h3>Start with absence management</h3>
<p>If you are still using phone trees or manual processes, this is your highest-priority investment. The ROI is immediate: faster fills, less administrative time, and better data.</p>
<h3>Add performance tracking next</h3>
<p>Once your absence management system is running, layer on feedback collection. This requires minimal technology investment but produces significant intelligence about your pool.</p>
<h3>Build the dashboard third</h3>
<p>Once you have absence and performance data flowing, build a dashboard. Even a manual weekly update takes only 30 minutes and provides visibility that transforms decision-making.</p>
<h3>Add communication last</h3>
<p>Communication tools are valuable but less urgent. You can send emails and make phone calls in the meantime. The dedicated communication platform is an efficiency upgrade, not a capability gap.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>System adoption rate</strong> (are teachers and subs using the platform?)</li>
<li><strong>Notification response rate</strong> (how quickly do subs respond to assignment offers?)</li>
<li><strong>Fill rate change post-implementation</strong> (track for at least 6 months)</li>
<li><strong>Administrative time savings</strong> (hours per week freed by the platform)</li>
<li><strong>Survey completion rate</strong> (are teachers providing post-assignment feedback?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Buying the most expensive platform without defining needs.</strong> Features you do not use are not worth paying for. Start with your requirements.</li>
<li><strong>Implementing without training.</strong> A powerful platform that nobody knows how to use delivers zero value. Invest in training for all user groups.</li>
<li><strong>Not cleaning data before migration.</strong> Moving dirty data into a new system creates dirty results faster. Clean your sub pool data first.</li>
<li><strong>Expecting technology to fix process problems.</strong> If your substitute program has structural issues (bad building experiences, low pay, no quality management), technology will run a broken process more efficiently. Fix the process too.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>CoSN, &quot;Technology for K-12 Staffing&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>Frontline Education, &quot;Absence Management Technology Guide&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>EdSurge, &quot;The State of EdTech in K-12 Operations&quot; (2024).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Map your current substitute management process from absence report to assignment confirmation. Count the manual steps. Identify the three most time-consuming ones. Those are your technology investment priorities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Substitute Teaching</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Measure Whether Your Extended Learning Program Is Actually Working]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/measuring-extended-learning-program-success.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/measuring-extended-learning-program-success.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[You are running an after-school or summer program. You think it is working. But how do you know? Here is a practical measurement framework for extended learning.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most extended learning programs can tell you how many students are enrolled. Many can tell you the average attendance. Very few can tell you whether the program is actually improving student outcomes. This is a problem. Without measurement, you cannot improve. Without evidence, you cannot justify continued investment. And without data, every conversation about your program is based on anecdotes and hope.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Effective extended learning program evaluation measures outcomes at three levels: participation (are students attending?), quality (is the program well-implemented?), and impact (are student outcomes improving?). Most programs only measure participation. The strongest programs use a combination of attendance data, implementation observations, student growth metrics (academic and non-academic), and comparison to non-participants. A practical evaluation does not require a research team. It requires consistent data collection on a few key indicators, reviewed regularly and used to make program adjustments.</p>
</div>

<h2>The three levels of measurement</h2>
<h3>Level 1: Participation</h3>
<p>This is the foundation. If students are not attending, nothing else matters.</p>
<p><strong>What to measure:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Daily attendance rate</li>
<li>Attendance trend over time (is it stable, improving, or declining?)</li>
<li>Dosage (total hours of programming each student receives)</li>
<li>Enrollment vs. consistent attendance (how many enrolled students attend at least 75% of sessions?)</li>
</ul>
<p>Participation data is easy to collect and should be reviewed weekly. A declining attendance trend is an early warning that requires immediate investigation.</p>
<h3>Level 2: Quality</h3>
<p>A program can have high attendance and low quality. Measuring quality means assessing whether the program is being delivered as intended and whether the experience is engaging.</p>
<p><strong>What to measure:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Implementation fidelity (is the curriculum being followed? Are activities delivered as designed?)</li>
<li>Staff quality (observation ratings, qualifications, retention)</li>
<li>Student engagement (observed engagement during activities, not just physical presence)</li>
<li>Student and family satisfaction (brief surveys, two to three questions)</li>
</ul>
<p>Quality measurement requires periodic observation, ideally once per month. Create a simple observation rubric: engagement level, activity quality, staff-student interaction, and time on task.</p>
<h3>Level 3: Impact</h3>
<p>This is where most programs struggle. Measuring impact means determining whether students who participate in the program show better outcomes than they would have without it.</p>
<p><strong>What to measure:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Academic growth (using assessments that students take regardless of program participation, like district benchmarks)</li>
<li>School-day attendance (do program participants attend school more regularly?)</li>
<li>Behavioral indicators (discipline referrals, suspensions)</li>
<li>Social-emotional skills (survey-based measures)</li>
<li>Grade promotion and graduation rates (for older students)</li>
</ul>
<p>Impact measurement is more complex because it requires a comparison. The simplest approach: compare outcomes for program participants to outcomes for similar students who did not participate. Match on prior achievement and grade level.</p>
<h2>Building a practical evaluation</h2>
<h3>Start with what you have</h3>
<p>You do not need new assessments. Use existing district data: benchmark assessments, attendance records, discipline logs, and report card grades. Pulling this data for program participants and a comparison group gives you impact estimates without administering a single additional test.</p>
<h3>Collect satisfaction data monthly</h3>
<p>A three-question student survey takes two minutes and provides real-time feedback:</p>
<ol>
<li>Did you enjoy today&#39;s activities? (Yes / Somewhat / No)</li>
<li>Did you learn something new today? (Yes / Somewhat / No)</li>
<li>What would make this program better? (Open response)</li>
</ol>
<p>Review responses monthly. Act on patterns. When students consistently say they want more hands-on activities and less lecture, adjust.</p>
<h3>Observe quality quarterly</h3>
<p>Four times per year, a program administrator should observe each program site using a standardized rubric. Rate: student engagement, activity quality, staff preparation, and time management. Share results with staff and discuss improvement strategies.</p>
<h3>Report impact annually</h3>
<p>At the end of each program year, compile the impact analysis. Compare participant outcomes to matched non-participants on academic, attendance, and behavioral metrics. Present the findings to district leadership and funders.</p>
<h3>Use data to improve, not just report</h3>
<p>The point of evaluation is improvement, not just accountability. Monthly attendance and satisfaction data should trigger immediate program adjustments. Quarterly observation data should inform professional development. Annual impact data should shape next year&#39;s program design.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Attendance rate and trend</strong> (weekly review)</li>
<li><strong>Dosage per student</strong> (total hours, target a minimum threshold)</li>
<li><strong>Student satisfaction</strong> (monthly survey)</li>
<li><strong>Implementation quality</strong> (quarterly observation)</li>
<li><strong>Academic and behavioral impact</strong> (annual comparison analysis)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Measuring only attendance.</strong> Attendance is necessary but not sufficient. Students can attend a low-quality program every day and gain nothing.</li>
<li><strong>Not having a comparison group.</strong> Without comparison, you cannot distinguish program impact from normal student growth.</li>
<li><strong>Surveying students once a year.</strong> Annual surveys capture a snapshot. Monthly surveys capture trends and enable real-time improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Reporting data without using it.</strong> If evaluation data does not change program practice, it is a compliance exercise, not an improvement tool.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;Evaluating Extended Learning Programs&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>Harvard Family Research Project, &quot;Evaluating Out-of-School Time Programs&quot; (2019).</li>
<li>American Institutes for Research, &quot;After-School Program Quality Assessment&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Identify the two assessments your district already administers to all students (likely a reading and math benchmark). Pull last year&#39;s results for your program participants and a matched group of non-participants. Compare the growth. That analysis, which takes about an hour, is the beginning of your impact story.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Gary Henderson</author>
            <category>Extended Learning</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Turning Paraprofessionals into Teachers: A Step-by-Step Pipeline Guide]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/paraprofessional-to-teacher-pipeline.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/paraprofessional-to-teacher-pipeline.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Your paraprofessionals already know your students, your schools, and your culture. Here's how to create a structured pathway from paraprofessional to certified teacher.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are roughly 1.3 million paraprofessionals working in American schools. They are in your classrooms right now. They know your students by name. They understand your community. They have chosen to work in education despite earning a fraction of teacher pay. And many of them want to teach.</p>
<p>The paraprofessional-to-teacher pipeline is the most underused recruitment strategy in K-12 education. Not because it is new. Because most districts have never built the structure to make it work.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Paraprofessional-to-teacher pipeline programs convert existing school employees into certified teachers by providing financial support, flexible coursework, and mentoring through the certification process. Research shows that teachers who enter through paraprofessional pipelines stay in their districts 2-3 times longer than externally recruited teachers and bring deep knowledge of the community and student population they serve. Effective programs take three to five years from enrollment to certification and require sustained district investment of $10,000-$20,000 per participant.</p>
</div>

<h2>Why this pipeline works</h2>
<h3>They already chose education</h3>
<p>A paraprofessional earning $28,000 per year has already demonstrated that they value working with students enough to accept below-market pay. That intrinsic motivation is exactly what drives long-term retention as a teacher.</p>
<h3>They know the work</h3>
<p>By the time a paraprofessional earns their teaching credential, they have spent years in actual classrooms. They have managed student behavior, supported instruction, and navigated school systems. Their first year as a certified teacher is their first year with full responsibility, not their first year in a school.</p>
<h3>They reflect the community</h3>
<p>Paraprofessionals are often bilingual and deeply rooted in the local community. Converting them to teachers strengthens the connection between your teaching staff and the families you serve.</p>
<h2>Building the pipeline step by step</h2>
<h3>Step 1: Identify interested paraprofessionals</h3>
<p>Survey your paraprofessional workforce. Ask directly: &quot;Are you interested in becoming a certified teacher? What barriers stand in your way?&quot; Most districts are surprised by the number of paraprofessionals who express interest and by the consistency of the barriers they identify.</p>
<p>The most common barriers: cost of tuition, inability to attend daytime classes while working, lack of information about certification pathways, and concerns about being able to handle the academic demands.</p>
<h3>Step 2: Partner with a university or alternative certification program</h3>
<p>You need an accredited partner to provide coursework and supervised clinical experience. Look for programs that offer evening, weekend, or online coursework. Programs designed for working adults with flexible scheduling are essential because your participants cannot quit their jobs to attend school full-time.</p>
<p>Negotiate group enrollment rates. A cohort of 10 paraprofessionals has more bargaining power than 10 individual applicants.</p>
<h3>Step 3: Structure the financial support</h3>
<p>The financial model is the make-or-break factor. Options include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Full tuition reimbursement</strong> in exchange for a three-to-five year teaching commitment after certification</li>
<li><strong>Partial tuition reimbursement</strong> (50-75%) with the participant covering the remainder</li>
<li><strong>Stipend model</strong> providing a monthly stipend during the program to offset lost income from additional hours spent on coursework</li>
<li><strong>Loan forgiveness</strong> leveraging state and federal loan forgiveness programs for teachers in high-need areas</li>
</ul>
<p>Calculate the total cost per participant. For most programs, this ranges from $10,000 to $20,000 over three to five years. Compare this to the cost of recruiting, hiring, and potentially replacing an externally hired teacher who leaves after two years.</p>
<h3>Step 4: Provide academic and emotional support</h3>
<p>Participants who have been out of college for years, or who never attended college, need support. Assign each participant a mentor. Create a study group among the cohort. Offer academic tutoring for challenging coursework. Provide emotional support for the imposter syndrome that many paraprofessionals experience when they enter a certification program.</p>
<p>The cohort model is powerful. Participants who go through the program together support each other, hold each other accountable, and celebrate each other&#39;s milestones.</p>
<h3>Step 5: Create a transition plan</h3>
<p>As participants near certification, plan their transition from paraprofessional to teacher. Identify the position they will fill. Introduce them to their new team. Provide an extended mentoring period during their first year as a certified teacher. The transition should feel like a graduation, not a cold start.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Program enrollment vs. completion rate</strong> (what percentage of participants earn certification?)</li>
<li><strong>Time to certification</strong> (average years from enrollment to credential)</li>
<li><strong>Retention rate at 3 and 5 years</strong> (compare to externally hired teachers)</li>
<li><strong>Community connection</strong> (are pipeline graduates from the local community?)</li>
<li><strong>Cost per certified teacher</strong> (total program investment divided by completers)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Underinvesting financially.</strong> A $1,000 annual stipend is not enough. If the financial support does not meaningfully reduce the barrier, participants will drop out.</li>
<li><strong>Choosing a rigid university partner.</strong> Programs that require daytime attendance or full-time enrollment will not work for employed paraprofessionals.</li>
<li><strong>Not providing academic support.</strong> Participants who struggle academically and receive no support leave the program feeling like failures. Tutoring and mentoring prevent this.</li>
<li><strong>Forgetting the transition.</strong> A paraprofessional who earns certification and is dropped into a classroom with no additional support faces the same first-year challenges as any new teacher. Provide a smooth transition.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>New America, &quot;From Paraprofessional to Teacher&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>Learning Policy Institute, &quot;Diversifying the Teaching Profession&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>Center for American Progress, &quot;Paraprofessional-to-Teacher Pipelines&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Send a one-question survey to every paraprofessional in your district: &quot;If financial and schedule barriers were removed, would you be interested in becoming a certified teacher?&quot; The response rate and the answers will tell you whether you have a pipeline opportunity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Teacher Recruitment</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How District Leadership Can Drive Better Staffing Outcomes]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/district-leadership-and-staffing-outcomes.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/district-leadership-and-staffing-outcomes.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Superintendent priorities, board decisions, and central office culture shape every staffing metric in your district. Here is how strong leaders make the difference.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When staffing challenges arise, the conversation usually focuses on market conditions: not enough teachers, not enough subs, salaries too low. These are real factors. But I have seen districts in the same labor market achieve very different staffing outcomes. The variable that often makes the difference is how leadership approaches the challenge.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>District-level leadership decisions, including strategic priorities, budget allocation, organizational culture, and superintendent focus, directly influence teacher recruitment, retention, substitute fill rates, and overall staffing health. Research shows that districts where the superintendent publicly prioritizes staffing and allocates dedicated resources to workforce strategy outperform similar districts by 10-20% on key staffing metrics. The mechanism is straightforward: when leadership prioritizes staffing, it gets the resources, attention, and follow-through needed to produce results.</p>
</div>

<h2>The leadership-staffing connection</h2>
<h3>Budget allocation reveals priorities</h3>
<p>Where the money goes reflects what leadership values. Dedicating budget to staffing initiatives sends a clear signal that workforce health is a priority.</p>
<p>Staffing deserves a dedicated budget line. Recruitment marketing, substitute incentives, mentorship program coordination, professional development, and retention initiatives all cost money. They also save money by reducing the far larger costs of turnover, uncovered classrooms, and chronic understaffing.</p>
<h3>Organizational culture flows from the top</h3>
<p>A superintendent who talks about teachers as professionals creates a culture where teachers are treated as professionals. When leadership frames staffing as a strategic priority rather than a compliance function, HR teams are empowered to build real workforce strategy.</p>
<p>The language leadership uses about staffing matters. The meetings leadership schedules about staffing matters. The data leadership asks to see about staffing matters. All of these signals cascade through the organization.</p>
<h3>Board engagement enables or constrains</h3>
<p>School boards that understand the connection between staffing and student outcomes are more likely to approve competitive compensation, invest in recruitment technology, and support innovative programs like grow-your-own initiatives. Boards that see the staffing-outcomes connection are powerful allies in building a strong workforce.</p>
<p>Superintendents who educate their boards about staffing metrics and their connection to educational outcomes create the conditions for better staffing decisions.</p>
<h2>What effective staffing leadership looks like</h2>
<h3>1. Staffing is a standing agenda item</h3>
<p>In high-performing districts, staffing metrics appear on the superintendent&#39;s dashboard alongside academic metrics. Vacancy rates, fill rates, retention data, and pipeline indicators are reviewed monthly, not annually.</p>
<h3>2. Dedicated staffing strategy role</h3>
<p>Someone in the district, not the HR director who also handles benefits, compliance, and grievances, owns workforce strategy as their primary responsibility. This person analyzes data, coordinates recruitment, manages the substitute program, and reports directly to senior leadership.</p>
<h3>3. Principal accountability for retention</h3>
<p>Principals are evaluated, in part, on teacher retention at their building. This creates alignment: principals who are accountable for retention invest in the culture, support, and working conditions that keep teachers.</p>
<h3>4. Investment in data infrastructure</h3>
<p>Districts cannot manage what they do not measure. Leadership that invests in staffing data systems, even simple ones, makes better decisions. A weekly dashboard showing fill rates, active pool size, and vacancy trends enables responsive management rather than reactive crisis management.</p>
<h3>5. External orientation</h3>
<p>Effective leaders stay connected to the labor market, to what other districts are doing, to what research says, and to what emerging trends suggest about the future of K-12 staffing. Insular leadership makes decisions based on internal assumptions. Externally oriented leadership makes decisions based on reality.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Staffing metric review frequency</strong> (how often does the superintendent review staffing data?)</li>
<li><strong>Budget allocation for staffing</strong> (what percentage of the HR budget is dedicated to recruitment and retention vs. compliance?)</li>
<li><strong>Principal retention accountability</strong> (is retention part of principal evaluation?)</li>
<li><strong>Board engagement</strong> (how often does the board receive staffing updates?)</li>
<li><strong>Competitive position</strong> (does leadership know how the district compares to nearby districts on key staffing metrics?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Treating staffing as purely administrative.</strong> Staffing is a strategic function. When leadership is involved, outcomes improve.</li>
<li><strong>Reviewing staffing data only during crises.</strong> Regular data review enables proactive management and prevents emergencies.</li>
<li><strong>Not sharing staffing data with the board.</strong> Boards respond to data. Connecting staffing stability to student outcomes builds support for investment.</li>
<li><strong>Focusing only on market conditions.</strong> Market conditions matter, but leadership strategy determines how well a district performs within its market.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>AASA, &quot;The Superintendent&#39;s Role in Workforce Strategy&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>Wallace Foundation, &quot;The School Principal as Leader&quot; (2013).</li>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;District-Level Factors in Staffing&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Look at your next leadership team meeting agenda. Is staffing on it? If not, add three metrics: current vacancy count, month-over-month fill rate trend, and active substitute pool size. Putting staffing on the agenda is the first step to making it a priority.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Leadership and Culture</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building Community Partnerships That Solve Your Staffing Problems]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/building-community-partnerships-for-staffing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/building-community-partnerships-for-staffing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Your community has untapped talent that can fill classrooms, support programs, and strengthen schools. Here's how to build the partnerships that unlock it.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>School districts tend to think of staffing as an internal problem. HR recruits, HR hires, HR manages. But the reality is that your community contains enormous untapped potential: retired professionals who would love to mentor students, university students who need field experience, nonprofit organizations with trained youth workers, and businesses with employees looking for meaningful volunteer opportunities.</p>
<p>The districts that are solving their staffing challenges most creatively are the ones that look beyond their own walls.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Community partnerships can supplement district staffing in three ways: providing direct classroom support (substitute teachers, tutors, guest instructors), expanding extended learning program capacity (after-school and summer staff), and building long-term teacher pipelines (grow-your-own programs through university and community college partnerships). Effective partnerships are formalized with written agreements, have clear expectations for both parties, include training and onboarding for community partners, and are managed by a designated district staff member. Informal, ad-hoc partnerships consistently underperform structured ones.</p>
</div>

<h2>Types of partnerships that deliver staffing value</h2>
<h3>University partnerships</h3>
<p>Local universities and community colleges are your most valuable staffing partner. Student teachers need placements. Education students need field experience. Graduate students need research sites. In exchange, you get classroom support, potential future hires, and a direct pipeline to your applicant pool.</p>
<p>Build these partnerships proactively. Do not wait for the university to place student teachers at your schools. Reach out to the education department. Offer your schools as preferred placement sites. Create a positive student teacher experience that makes graduates want to apply when they earn their credential.</p>
<p>Extend beyond education departments. Nursing students can support school health offices. Social work students can join student support teams. Business students can help with operations and technology.</p>
<h3>Nonprofit and community organization partnerships</h3>
<p>Local nonprofits often employ or recruit the same populations you are trying to reach: youth workers, tutors, mentors, and program facilitators. Rather than competing for the same talent, partner to share it.</p>
<p>An after-school program run jointly by the district and a local youth organization combines the district&#39;s facilities and curriculum knowledge with the organization&#39;s staffing capacity and youth development expertise. Both are stronger together than separately.</p>
<h3>Business and industry partnerships</h3>
<p>Local businesses can provide: guest instructors for career and technical education, mentors for student programs, volunteers for school events, and financial support for staffing initiatives. In return, they access future workforce talent, fulfill corporate social responsibility goals, and build brand presence in the community.</p>
<p>Structure these partnerships with clear expectations. A business that provides a monthly guest speaker is a partnership. A business that provides three trained tutors for 10 hours per week is a staffing solution.</p>
<h3>Retiree engagement programs</h3>
<p>Your community&#39;s retired professionals, especially retired teachers, represent a largely untapped staffing resource. Retired teachers make exceptional substitutes, tutors, and mentors. Retired professionals from other fields bring subject matter expertise and life experience that enriches classrooms.</p>
<p>Create a formal retiree engagement program. Recruit through senior centers, retirement communities, and community organizations. Offer flexible, low-commitment entry points: one day per week, a specific program, a seasonal commitment. Remove barriers to participation: streamlined background checks, simple onboarding, and respectful scheduling.</p>
<h2>Making partnerships work</h2>
<h3>Formalize everything</h3>
<p>A handshake agreement is not a partnership. Write a memorandum of understanding that specifies: what each party provides, the timeline and commitment, training and supervision responsibilities, liability and insurance coverage, and communication protocols. This prevents misunderstandings and ensures continuity when individual contacts change.</p>
<h3>Designate a partnership manager</h3>
<p>Someone in the district should own community partnerships as part of their role. This person maintains relationships, coordinates logistics, tracks outcomes, and troubleshoots problems. Without a designated owner, partnerships decay through neglect.</p>
<h3>Train community partners</h3>
<p>A community volunteer in your school needs basic training: building procedures, student interaction guidelines, confidentiality expectations, and emergency protocols. Investing two hours in training prevents problems and signals that you take the partnership seriously.</p>
<h3>Measure and communicate impact</h3>
<p>Track what partnerships deliver: volunteer hours, tutoring sessions, substitute days filled, program capacity expanded. Share these numbers with partners and the community. Public recognition of partners&#39; contributions strengthens the relationship and attracts new partners.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Partnership inventory</strong> (how many active partnerships, and what does each provide?)</li>
<li><strong>Staffing hours contributed by partners</strong> (convert to FTE equivalent for context)</li>
<li><strong>Partner satisfaction</strong> (are partners finding the relationship valuable?)</li>
<li><strong>Pipeline conversion</strong> (how many university interns become applicants? How many volunteers become subs?)</li>
<li><strong>Cost avoidance</strong> (what would the district spend to replace partner-provided services?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Treating partnerships as charity.</strong> Effective partnerships benefit both sides. Understand what your partner wants and deliver it.</li>
<li><strong>Failing to formalize agreements.</strong> Informal partnerships collapse when the champion on either side moves on. Write it down.</li>
<li><strong>Not training community partners.</strong> An untrained volunteer in a classroom can create more problems than they solve.</li>
<li><strong>Expecting partners to manage themselves.</strong> Community partnerships require active district management. Designate a point person.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Coalition for Community Schools, &quot;Community Partnerships Framework&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>National Center for Community Schools, &quot;Staffing Through Partnerships&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>AASA, &quot;Community Engagement for Superintendent Success&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> List every community organization within five miles of your schools. Circle the three that employ or engage people who could support your staffing needs. Call one of them this week and ask: &quot;How can we work together?&quot;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Gary Henderson</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Calculate the Right Size for Your Substitute Teacher Pool]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/substitute-teacher-pool-size-calculator.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/substitute-teacher-pool-size-calculator.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Too small and you can't fill positions. Too large and you can't manage quality. Here's how to calculate the optimal substitute pool size for your district.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&quot;How many subs do we need?&quot; is a question I get constantly, and the answer is always &quot;it depends.&quot; But it depends on factors you can measure, which means you can calculate a specific number rather than guessing. Most districts either have too few subs (resulting in low fill rates) or too many on their roster (creating the illusion of capacity while most subs are inactive).</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>The optimal substitute pool size is determined by four factors: your average daily teacher absences, your target fill rate, your pool activation rate (the percentage of rostered subs who actually accept assignments regularly), and your peak absence multiplier. The formula is: Target Pool Size = (Peak Daily Absences x Target Fill Rate) / Pool Activation Rate. For example, a district with 50 peak daily absences, a 90% fill rate target, and a 40% pool activation rate needs 113 active subs on the roster. Most districts underestimate the activation rate gap: having 200 subs on paper means nothing if only 80 accept assignments regularly.</p>
</div>

<h2>The four inputs you need</h2>
<h3>1. Average daily absences</h3>
<p>Pull absence data from the previous year. Calculate the average number of teacher absences per day. Then calculate the peak: the highest single day and the average of the top 10% of absence days. Your pool needs to handle the peak, not the average.</p>
<p>Most districts find their peak absence days are 40-60% higher than their average. If your average is 30 absences per day, your peak days likely hit 42-48.</p>
<h3>2. Target fill rate</h3>
<p>What percentage of absences do you want covered by a substitute? Most districts target 85-95%. A 100% target is unrealistic due to same-day absences, hard-to-fill positions, and days when even large pools are fully utilized.</p>
<p>Set your target based on what is acceptable for your schools. Below 80% creates chronic coverage problems. Above 95% requires a very large, active pool.</p>
<h3>3. Pool activation rate</h3>
<p>This is the most important and most misunderstood number. Of all the subs on your roster, what percentage accept at least one assignment per month? In most districts, this number is 30-50%. A roster of 200 subs with a 35% activation rate is functionally a pool of 70.</p>
<p>Measure this by reviewing assignment data. Count the number of unique subs who accepted at least one assignment in the last 30 days. Divide by total rostered subs. That is your activation rate.</p>
<h3>4. Peak absence multiplier</h3>
<p>Your pool needs to handle not just average days but the worst days. Apply a multiplier based on your peak-to-average ratio. If your peak absence days are 50% higher than average, your multiplier is 1.5.</p>
<h2>Running the calculation</h2>
<h3>The formula</h3>
<p><strong>Target Pool Size = (Peak Daily Absences x Target Fill Rate) / Pool Activation Rate</strong></p>
<h3>Example: Medium-sized district</h3>
<ul>
<li>Average daily absences: 35</li>
<li>Peak daily absences (top 10% average): 52</li>
<li>Target fill rate: 90%</li>
<li>Pool activation rate: 40%</li>
</ul>
<p>Target Pool Size = (52 x 0.90) / 0.40 = 117 subs</p>
<p>This district needs 117 subs on the roster to cover 90% of absences on peak days, given that only 40% of rostered subs are regularly active.</p>
<h3>Example: Small district</h3>
<ul>
<li>Average daily absences: 8</li>
<li>Peak daily absences: 14</li>
<li>Target fill rate: 85%</li>
<li>Pool activation rate: 50%</li>
</ul>
<p>Target Pool Size = (14 x 0.85) / 0.50 = 24 subs</p>
<p>Smaller districts need proportionally larger activation rates because the margin for error is smaller. One inactive sub in a 24-person pool has more impact than one in a 117-person pool.</p>
<h2>What to do with the number</h2>
<h3>If your pool is too small</h3>
<p>Recruit aggressively. Focus on the channels that produce the most active subs, not just the most applications. A sub who signs up and never works does not help your numbers.</p>
<h3>If your pool is the right size but your activation rate is low</h3>
<p>The problem is not pool size. It is engagement. Survey inactive subs. Why did they stop accepting assignments? Bad experiences? Low pay? Scheduling conflicts? Address the root cause rather than recruiting replacements who will become inactive for the same reasons.</p>
<h3>If your pool is too large (on paper) but fill rates are low</h3>
<p>Your activation rate is the problem. A bloated roster of inactive subs creates a false sense of security. Focus on activating existing subs rather than adding more names to a list nobody checks.</p>
<h3>Recalculate every semester</h3>
<p>Absence patterns change. Sub pool composition changes. Activation rates fluctuate. Recalculate your target pool size at the start of each semester and adjust your recruitment and retention strategies accordingly.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rostered pool size vs. active pool size</strong> (close the gap between paper and reality)</li>
<li><strong>Pool activation rate</strong> (track monthly, target 50%+)</li>
<li><strong>Peak day coverage</strong> (what is your fill rate on the 10 worst absence days?)</li>
<li><strong>Recruitment yield</strong> (of new subs onboarded, what percentage become active within 30 days?)</li>
<li><strong>Pool composition</strong> (full-time subs, part-time, retired teachers, college students, etc.)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Confusing rostered pool size with active pool size.</strong> The number that matters is how many subs actually work, not how many are on the list.</li>
<li><strong>Sizing for average days instead of peak days.</strong> Average days are manageable. Peak days break your system. Size for the peak.</li>
<li><strong>Not tracking activation rate.</strong> If you do not know what percentage of your pool is active, you cannot assess whether your pool is adequate.</li>
<li><strong>Recruiting without retaining.</strong> Adding 50 new subs while losing 40 existing ones nets you 10. Fix retention before scaling recruitment.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Frontline Education, &quot;Substitute Pool Optimization&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>AASPA, &quot;Workforce Planning for Substitute Programs&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>Kelly Education, &quot;Pool Size and Fill Rate Analysis&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Calculate your pool activation rate. Pull the list of every rostered sub. Count how many accepted at least one assignment in the last 30 days. Divide. If the number is below 40%, your pool is smaller than you think, and your fill rate reflects the active pool, not the roster.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Teacher Exit Interview Questions That Actually Reveal Why They're Leaving]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-exit-interview-questions.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/teacher-exit-interview-questions.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Most exit interviews produce polite non-answers. These questions get to the real reasons teachers leave, and give you data you can act on.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&quot;Why are you leaving?&quot; &quot;I got a better opportunity.&quot; &quot;What could we have done differently?&quot; &quot;Nothing, it was just time.&quot; &quot;Would you recommend this district?&quot; &quot;Of course.&quot;</p>
<p>That is how most teacher exit interviews go. The departing teacher is polite, vague, and eager to leave on good terms. The district learns nothing actionable. The same problems that drove the teacher out continue driving others out. The cycle repeats.</p>
<p>Exit interviews can be the most valuable data source a district has for understanding and reducing turnover. But only if you ask the right questions in the right way.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Effective teacher exit interviews produce actionable data about the specific, addressable factors that drive turnover. The keys to getting honest, useful responses are: conducting the interview after the teacher&#39;s last day (when they no longer fear consequences), asking specific behavioral questions rather than general opinion questions, using a consistent protocol across all exits, and assuring confidentiality of individual responses while aggregating themes for leadership. Districts that implement structured exit interview programs identify building-specific retention problems, systemic issues, and fixable dissatisfiers that generic surveys miss.</p>
</div>

<h2>Why most exit interviews fail</h2>
<h3>They happen too early</h3>
<p>An interview on the teacher&#39;s last day, while they are still navigating final paperwork and maintaining relationships, produces diplomatic answers. Conduct the interview two to four weeks after departure. The teacher is emotionally detached enough to be honest and far enough removed to have perspective.</p>
<h3>They ask the wrong questions</h3>
<p>&quot;Why are you leaving?&quot; invites a single, simple answer: money, location, opportunity. The real reasons are almost always more complex and more useful. Replace broad questions with specific ones that probe actual experiences and decisions.</p>
<h3>The data is not always acted upon</h3>
<p>Exit interview responses are most valuable when they inform action. Aggregate exit data quarterly. Identify patterns. Report findings to district leadership. Assign someone to act on the findings.</p>
<h2>The questions that reveal the truth</h2>
<h3>About their daily experience</h3>
<p><strong>&quot;Describe a typical Tuesday in your school. Walk me through the day.&quot;</strong> This question reveals workload, time usage, and daily satisfaction without asking directly about any of them. Listen for: how much time is spent on instruction vs. non-instructional tasks, the level of autonomy, the pace and stress level.</p>
<p><strong>&quot;What was the best part of your week, most weeks?&quot;</strong> This reveals what kept them coming back, and by implication, what was not strong enough to retain them.</p>
<p><strong>&quot;What was the most frustrating recurring problem you faced?&quot;</strong> &quot;Recurring&quot; is the key word. One-time frustrations are forgettable. Recurring ones drive people out.</p>
<h3>About leadership and support</h3>
<p><strong>&quot;When you needed support from your administration, what did that look like? Can you give me a specific example?&quot;</strong> Specific examples reveal whether support was real or theoretical. Listen for: response time, follow-through, and whether the teacher felt backed up.</p>
<p><strong>&quot;How were decisions made that affected your work? Were you consulted?&quot;</strong> This reveals whether teachers had voice. Listen for: top-down vs. collaborative decision-making, whether input was solicited, whether input mattered.</p>
<h3>About the decision to leave</h3>
<p><strong>&quot;When did you first start thinking about leaving? What was happening at that time?&quot;</strong> The timing reveals the trigger. Was it September exhaustion? January burnout? A specific event? A change in circumstances? The trigger is often the most actionable piece of data.</p>
<p><strong>&quot;What would have needed to change for you to stay?&quot;</strong> This is the gold question. It reveals the specific, often fixable factor that tipped the decision. &quot;If I had 15 fewer students in my class.&quot; &quot;If my principal had supported me with that parent.&quot; &quot;If I had one more planning period per week.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>&quot;If a friend were considering a job in this district, what would you tell them honestly?&quot;</strong> This question, asked last, often produces the most candid assessment of the district.</p>
<h3>About what comes next</h3>
<p><strong>&quot;What does your new position offer that this one did not?&quot;</strong> The comparison reveals the specific gaps: salary, working conditions, support, growth opportunities, or something else entirely.</p>
<h2>Processing and using exit data</h2>
<h3>Aggregate quarterly</h3>
<p>Individual exit interviews are anecdotes. Aggregated exit data is intelligence. Every quarter, compile the responses. Code them by theme: workload, leadership, compensation, working conditions, growth opportunities. Identify the top three themes.</p>
<h3>Report to leadership</h3>
<p>Present aggregated exit data to district leadership quarterly. Protect individual confidentiality but share the patterns. &quot;Twelve of our 18 departing teachers cited lack of administrative support as a factor. Six specifically mentioned the same building.&quot;</p>
<h3>Track changes over time</h3>
<p>Are the same themes appearing year after year? That indicates systemic issues that are not being addressed. Are new themes emerging? That might indicate a response to recent policy changes.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exit interview completion rate</strong> (what percentage of departing teachers participate?)</li>
<li><strong>Top three departure themes by quarter</strong> (are they consistent or changing?)</li>
<li><strong>Building-specific patterns</strong> (do exits cluster at particular schools?)</li>
<li><strong>Actionable findings per quarter</strong> (how many specific, implementable recommendations emerge?)</li>
<li><strong>Follow-through rate</strong> (of recommendations made, how many were acted on?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Conducting the interview on the last day.</strong> Wait two to four weeks. Candor increases with distance.</li>
<li><strong>Asking only &quot;why are you leaving?&quot;</strong> This produces a single, often misleading answer. Use multiple specific questions to get the full picture.</li>
<li><strong>Not aggregating the data.</strong> Individual interviews are stories. Aggregated data is strategy.</li>
<li><strong>Collecting data without acting on it.</strong> If exit interview themes persist for three consecutive quarters without response, the process is performative.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>SHRM, &quot;Conducting Effective Exit Interviews&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>Learning Policy Institute, &quot;Teacher Turnover: Why It Matters and What We Can Do About It&quot; (2017).</li>
<li>Ingersoll, R. M. (2001). &quot;Teacher Turnover and Teacher Shortages.&quot; American Educational Research Journal.</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Review the exit interview data from your last five departing teachers. If you do not have exit interview data, that is your first problem. If you do, identify the one theme that appears most often. That theme is where your retention strategy should start.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Teacher Retention</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Get Students to Actually Attend Summer School]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/summer-school-attendance-strategies.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/summer-school-attendance-strategies.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Summer school works when students show up. Most don't. Here are the enrollment and attendance strategies that separate effective programs from empty classrooms.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Summer school is mandatory for some students. Required by the district. Scheduled and staffed. And then half the students do not show up. This is not a new problem, but it is a deeply frustrating one. Districts invest significant resources in summer programming, and student no-shows turn that investment into empty chairs and wasted potential.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Summer school attendance rates average 60-70% nationally, meaning 30-40% of enrolled students do not attend consistently. The strongest predictors of summer attendance are: whether the student had input into their enrollment, how the first day is structured, transportation availability, and whether the program feels meaningfully different from the regular school year. Districts that achieve 80%+ summer attendance rates combine proactive family engagement before the program starts, transportation solutions, engaging programming that mixes academics with enrichment, and daily attendance tracking with immediate follow-up on absences.</p>
</div>

<h2>Why students skip summer school</h2>
<h3>It feels like punishment</h3>
<p>For students required to attend summer school for credit recovery or promotion, the program inherently feels punitive. &quot;You failed, so now you have to go to school during your break.&quot; Overcoming this perception requires the program to be genuinely different from the regular school year: different format, different pace, different activities.</p>
<h3>Transportation disappears</h3>
<p>During the school year, bus routes, parent schedules, and walking groups are established. Summer schedules disrupt all of these. A student who walked to school with friends in May has no walking group in July. The bus route that stopped at their corner does not run. Without transportation, attending becomes a daily logistics problem for families.</p>
<h3>There is nothing to come back for</h3>
<p>If Monday is worksheets and Tuesday is worksheets and Wednesday is worksheets, a student who misses Monday has no incentive to return Tuesday. Programs without engaging, varied activities lose students quickly because any given day feels replaceable.</p>
<h3>Families are not engaged</h3>
<p>Many families view summer school as the school&#39;s responsibility. They signed the enrollment form, and that is the extent of their involvement. Without ongoing family communication, summer school fades from priority as summer activities, vacations, and competing commitments take over.</p>
<h2>Strategies that drive summer attendance</h2>
<h3>1. Start family engagement before enrollment</h3>
<p>Do not wait until the enrollment form is sent home. Begin communicating about summer school in April. Host an informational evening. Show families what the program will look like: not more of the same, but something different and engaging. When families understand the value, they become attendance partners.</p>
<h3>2. Solve transportation first</h3>
<p>Survey families during enrollment about transportation needs. Provide bus routes, partner with community organizations for carpools, or offer transportation stipends for families who drive. A student without a reliable ride cannot attend no matter how much they want to.</p>
<h3>3. Front-load engagement</h3>
<p>Make the first three days the best three days. Lead with field trips, guest speakers, hands-on projects, and social activities. Students who enjoy the first week build the habit of attending. Students who endure a boring first week have no reason to return for a boring second week.</p>
<h3>4. Mix academics with enrichment daily</h3>
<p>The most effective summer programs do not separate academic blocks from enrichment blocks. They integrate them. A math lesson built around designing a garden. A reading lesson connected to a cooking project. A science unit that culminates in a field trip to a local lab.</p>
<p>When every day includes something students look forward to, daily attendance becomes self-reinforcing.</p>
<h3>5. Track and respond to absences immediately</h3>
<p>Call the family after the first missed day, not the third. &quot;We missed Jaylen today. Tomorrow we&#39;re starting our bridge-building project and we need him on his team.&quot; This message does two things: it communicates that someone noticed, and it gives a specific reason to come back tomorrow.</p>
<h3>6. Create social belonging</h3>
<p>Students are more likely to attend when they have friends in the program and feel part of a group. Create team structures on day one. Give teams names and identities. Build in social time. The social fabric of the program is an attendance driver that costs nothing.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enrollment-to-attendance conversion</strong> (percentage of enrolled students who attend day one)</li>
<li><strong>Daily attendance rate</strong> (track the trend line across the program)</li>
<li><strong>Week-over-week retention</strong> (what percentage of week one attendees are still attending in week three?)</li>
<li><strong>Attendance by transportation type</strong> (do students with bus access attend at higher rates?)</li>
<li><strong>Student satisfaction survey</strong> (weekly, two to three questions)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Making summer school feel identical to the regular school year.</strong> If students disengaged during the year, more of the same will not re-engage them in summer.</li>
<li><strong>Not providing transportation.</strong> This is the number one logistical barrier and must be solved before the program starts.</li>
<li><strong>Waiting to address non-attendance.</strong> By the time you notice a student has missed three days, they have mentally withdrawn. Call after day one.</li>
<li><strong>Treating enrollment as attendance.</strong> An enrolled student who does not show up received zero benefit from the program. Track actual attendance, not enrollment numbers.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>RAND Corporation, &quot;Making Summer Count&quot; (2020).</li>
<li>National Summer Learning Association, &quot;Summer Learning Program Quality Assessment&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>Wallace Foundation, &quot;Partnerships for Social and Emotional Learning&quot; (2022).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Pull your enrollment and attendance data from last summer. Calculate the percentage of enrolled students who attended at least 75% of sessions. If that number is below 60%, your program&#39;s impact is limited not by quality but by who is in the room. Solve attendance first.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Gary Henderson</author>
            <category>Extended Learning</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grow Your Own Teacher Programs: Building a Pipeline from Within]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/grow-your-own-teacher-programs.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/grow-your-own-teacher-programs.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The most committed teachers are the ones who grew up in your community. Grow-your-own programs turn paraprofessionals, students, and community members into your next generation of teachers.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The most retention-proof teachers are the ones with roots in the community. They went to school there. Their family lives there. They understand the culture, the challenges, and the strengths of the students because they share them. Grow-your-own programs do not just fill vacancies. They build a teaching workforce that reflects and is committed to the community it serves.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Grow-your-own (GYO) teacher programs recruit and support community members, including paraprofessionals, substitute teachers, high school students, and career changers, through a pathway to teaching certification. Research shows that GYO teachers are 2-3 times more likely to remain in their district after five years compared to externally recruited teachers. They are also deeply connected to the communities they serve. Effective GYO programs provide financial support (tuition reimbursement or scholarships), flexible coursework (evening and weekend classes), mentoring, and a service commitment to the sponsoring district.</p>
</div>

<h2>Four pathways that work</h2>
<h3>1. Paraprofessional to teacher</h3>
<p>Your paraprofessionals already know your schools, your students, and your systems. Many want to teach but cannot afford to stop working while earning a degree. A GYO program removes that barrier by providing tuition support, flexible scheduling, and a clear timeline from paraprofessional to certified teacher.</p>
<p>Typical structure: the district partners with a local university to offer evening and weekend coursework. Paraprofessionals continue working during the day. The district pays tuition, or a portion of it, in exchange for a three-to-five year teaching commitment after certification.</p>
<p>The pipeline is slower than external recruitment but produces teachers who stay. A paraprofessional who spent three years earning their teaching degree while working in your district is deeply invested in that district.</p>
<h3>2. High school cadet programs</h3>
<p>Identify high school students interested in teaching careers. Offer an education-focused pathway: teacher cadet courses, classroom observation opportunities, and dual enrollment in education coursework. Provide scholarships for students who attend a teacher preparation program and commit to returning to teach in the district.</p>
<p>This is a long-term investment. A student who enters the cadet program as a junior in high school is six to eight years from being a classroom teacher. But the yield rate on GYO high school programs is remarkably high because students self-select based on genuine interest.</p>
<h3>3. Substitute to teacher</h3>
<p>Your substitute pool contains people who are already in classrooms, already understand the work, and already know your schools. Some became subs because they were exploring a teaching career. Create a pathway for high-performing subs to earn certification while continuing to work as substitutes.</p>
<p>This pathway is particularly effective because subs accumulate real classroom experience along the way. By the time they earn certification, they have logged more classroom hours than most traditional student teachers.</p>
<h3>4. Career changer programs</h3>
<p>Partner with alternative certification programs to recruit career changers from your community. Target professionals with subject matter expertise: engineers for math and science, writers for English, businesspeople for CTE. Provide a bridge program that covers classroom management, pedagogy, and mentoring during their first year.</p>
<p>Career changers bring professional experience and maturity. With proper support, they can be highly effective teachers.</p>
<h2>Making GYO programs financially sustainable</h2>
<h3>Leverage state and federal funding</h3>
<p>Many states offer GYO grants specifically for districts developing local teacher pipelines. The federal TEACH grant provides up to $4,000 per year for students who commit to teaching in high-need schools. Research available funding before assuming the district must bear the full cost.</p>
<h3>Calculate the ROI</h3>
<p>A GYO teacher who costs $15,000 to develop (tuition, support, coordination) and stays for 10 years costs $1,500 per year. An externally recruited teacher who costs $5,000 to hire but leaves after two years, requiring another $5,000 to replace, costs $5,000 per year. The math overwhelmingly favors GYO when you account for retention.</p>
<h3>Start small</h3>
<p>You do not need to launch a 50-person program. Start with five paraprofessionals. Learn what works. Refine the model. Scale over three to five years. Small cohorts are easier to support, and early successes build institutional commitment.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>GYO completion rate</strong> (percentage of participants who earn certification)</li>
<li><strong>GYO retention rate at 3 and 5 years</strong> (compare to externally hired teachers)</li>
<li><strong>Community representation in GYO cohorts</strong> (does the pipeline reflect the student population?)</li>
<li><strong>Cost per GYO teacher vs. cost per externally recruited teacher</strong> (including turnover costs)</li>
<li><strong>Service commitment fulfillment rate</strong> (what percentage of GYO teachers complete their commitment?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Making the financial commitment inadequate.</strong> A $1,000 tuition stipend is not enough. If paraprofessionals still cannot afford the program, they will not enroll. Calculate the real financial barrier and address it.</li>
<li><strong>Not partnering with a university.</strong> GYO programs need an accredited partner to provide coursework and certification. Build the university relationship before recruiting candidates.</li>
<li><strong>Recruiting without support.</strong> Enrolling community members in a certification program without mentoring, coaching, and logistical support leads to high dropout rates.</li>
<li><strong>Expecting immediate results.</strong> GYO programs take three to five years to produce their first teachers. They are a long-term strategy, not a quick fix for this year&#39;s vacancies.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Learning Policy Institute, &quot;Grow Your Own Teacher Programs&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>New America, &quot;Grow Your Own Teachers: A 50-State Scan&quot; (2022).</li>
<li>Education Commission of the States, &quot;Grow Your Own Educator Policies&quot; (2024).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Identify five paraprofessionals in your district who have expressed interest in becoming teachers. Ask them what is standing in their way. Their answers will tell you exactly what your GYO program needs to address.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Teacher Recruitment</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Evaluate Staffing Technology Without Getting Sold]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/district-staffing-technology-evaluation.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/district-staffing-technology-evaluation.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[EdTech vendors promise everything. Here is a practical framework for evaluating staffing technology that focuses on what actually matters for your district.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Every week I talk to a district that just spent $100,000 on a staffing platform they do not use. The demo was impressive. The sales team was convincing. The contract was signed. Six months later, the system sits half-implemented while the office staff quietly returns to their spreadsheets and phone trees.</p>
<p>This is not a technology failure. It is an evaluation failure. The district bought a solution to a problem they had not fully defined, from a vendor they had not thoroughly vetted, with an implementation plan that did not account for their actual workflow.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>Effective staffing technology evaluation requires defining your specific problems before looking at solutions, involving end users in the evaluation process, testing with your actual data and workflows, and assessing the vendor&#39;s implementation support and track record with similar districts. The most common evaluation mistakes are: letting the vendor define the problem, evaluating features instead of outcomes, and failing to account for implementation complexity. A structured evaluation process takes four to six weeks and saves districts from six-figure mistakes.</p>
</div>

<h2>Before you look at a single product</h2>
<h3>Define the problem precisely</h3>
<p>&quot;We need better staffing software&quot; is not a problem statement. &quot;Our fill rate is 72%, and we believe the primary causes are slow notification speed, limited sub pool visibility, and inability to track preferences&quot; is a problem statement. The more precisely you define the problem, the more effectively you can evaluate whether a given solution addresses it.</p>
<h3>Identify your must-haves vs. nice-to-haves</h3>
<p>Create two lists. Must-haves are the features without which the system is a non-starter: integration with your HRIS, absence notification, mobile-friendly sub interface. Nice-to-haves are desirable but not required: advanced analytics, smart matching, custom reporting.</p>
<p>Most districts do the opposite: they create a wish list of every possible feature and evaluate vendors against a 50-item checklist. This leads to selecting the platform with the most features rather than the one that solves your specific problem.</p>
<h3>Map your current workflow</h3>
<p>Before evaluating new technology, document your current workflow in detail. How are absences reported? Who notifies subs? How are assignments confirmed? What happens when a position goes unfilled? Where are the bottlenecks?</p>
<p>This map serves two purposes: it helps you evaluate whether a new system actually improves your workflow, and it helps the vendor configure the system to match how your district operates.</p>
<h2>The evaluation process</h2>
<h3>1. Start with references, not demos</h3>
<p>Before watching a demo, ask the vendor for references from three districts similar to yours in size and context. Call those districts. Ask: What problem did this solve? What did implementation look like? What surprised you? Would you buy it again?</p>
<p>References provide ground truth that no demo can match. If a vendor cannot provide relevant references, that is a signal.</p>
<h3>2. Test with your own data</h3>
<p>A demo with perfect sample data always looks great. Request a pilot or proof of concept using your actual sub pool data, your actual absence patterns, and your actual building preferences. Seeing the system operate with your real-world complexity reveals issues that demo data hides.</p>
<h3>3. Involve the end users</h3>
<p>The people who will use the system daily, office staff, building secretaries, HR coordinators, should be in the evaluation from the start. Their feedback on usability, workflow fit, and practical limitations is more valuable than administrative assessment.</p>
<p>Ask end users: &quot;Would this make your job easier?&quot; If the answer is not an enthusiastic yes, the implementation will struggle.</p>
<h3>4. Evaluate the vendor, not just the product</h3>
<p>Technology is only as good as the support behind it. Assess the vendor on: implementation timeline and support, training resources, customer service responsiveness, product roadmap and update frequency, and financial stability.</p>
<p>A great product with poor implementation support will fail. A good product with excellent support will succeed.</p>
<h3>5. Negotiate the contract carefully</h3>
<p>Ensure the contract includes: a defined implementation timeline with milestones, training for all user groups, a trial period with the option to exit, clear pricing for the full term including any per-user or per-building fees, and data portability (you own your data).</p>
<p>Avoid multi-year contracts without exit clauses. The first year is a test. If the system does not deliver the expected outcomes, you should be able to leave.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Baseline metrics before implementation</strong> (fill rate, time to fill, admin hours spent, sub satisfaction)</li>
<li><strong>Same metrics at 90, 180, and 365 days post-implementation</strong> (is the system delivering improvement?)</li>
<li><strong>User adoption rate</strong> (what percentage of intended users are actually using the system?)</li>
<li><strong>Support ticket volume and resolution time</strong> (is the vendor responsive?)</li>
<li><strong>ROI calculation</strong> (cost of the system vs. measurable improvements in efficiency and outcomes)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Letting the vendor run the evaluation.</strong> They will show you what they want you to see. Control the process.</li>
<li><strong>Evaluating features instead of outcomes.</strong> A 50-feature checklist does not help. &quot;Will this improve our fill rate by 10 points?&quot; does.</li>
<li><strong>Not involving end users.</strong> Systems that administrators love but office staff hate get abandoned within months.</li>
<li><strong>Signing multi-year contracts before proving the system works.</strong> Negotiate a trial period. Protect your exit options.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>EdTech Evidence Exchange, &quot;Evaluating Education Technology&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>CoSN, &quot;Technology Purchasing Frameworks&quot; (2024).</li>
<li>AASA, &quot;Smart Procurement for School Districts&quot; (2023).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Write a one-paragraph problem statement describing your district&#39;s biggest staffing challenge. Be specific about the symptoms, the scale, and the impact. This paragraph is the starting point for any technology evaluation and will save you from buying a solution to the wrong problem.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Donnie Decker</author>
            <category>Staffing Operations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Every District Should Tell New Teachers Before Day One]]></title>
            <link>https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/new-teacher-first-year-survival-guide.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://spureducation.com/blog/posts/new-teacher-first-year-survival-guide.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[First-year teachers are overwhelmed before they even start. A structured onboarding process before school begins can prevent the most common early-career crises.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A new teacher walks into their classroom for the first time in August. They have a degree, a certification, student teaching experience, and absolutely no idea how to navigate the daily logistics of an actual school. Where do I make copies? How does the grade book work? What do I do when a student refuses to leave the room? Who do I call when the projector breaks?</p>
<p>These are not trivial questions. They are the questions that consume a new teacher&#39;s first weeks and months, crowd out instructional focus, and create the overwhelming feeling that leads 25% of new teachers to leave within three years.</p>
<div class="direct-answer">

<p>First-year teacher attrition is a significant and costly problem: approximately 10% of new teachers leave after their first year, and 25% leave within three years. Research shows that comprehensive onboarding before the school year starts, covering logistics, culture, curriculum, and relational support, significantly reduces early attrition. The most effective programs begin two to three weeks before the first student day and include building-specific orientation, mentorship pairing, curriculum overview, classroom setup time, and explicit instruction in the unwritten rules that veteran teachers take for granted.</p>
</div>

<h2>What new teachers need before day one</h2>
<h3>1. Building-specific logistics</h3>
<p>Every school has its own rhythms, systems, and unwritten rules. New teachers need a building orientation that covers: how to access the building before and after hours, copy machine procedures, supply request process, technology systems and passwords, discipline referral process, emergency procedures, and who to call for what.</p>
<p>Create a one-page &quot;who handles what&quot; directory. The copy machine is broken: call Dave. A student is in crisis: call Ms. Rodriguez. Your grade book is not working: email tech support at this address. This document alone reduces first-week anxiety dramatically.</p>
<h3>2. Curriculum orientation</h3>
<p>A new teacher needs to understand what they are teaching, what materials are available, and how their school approaches curriculum. Schedule time before school starts for new teachers to meet with grade-level or department colleagues. Walk through the first unit together. Show them where materials are located. Answer the questions they are afraid to ask in a larger group.</p>
<h3>3. Classroom setup time</h3>
<p>Give new teachers dedicated time to set up their classroom. This sounds simple, but many districts schedule new teacher orientation right up until the first student day, leaving no time for this essential preparation. New teachers who enter day one with an organized, personalized classroom feel more confident and in control.</p>
<h3>4. Mentor introduction and initial meeting</h3>
<p>Pair every new teacher with a mentor before the year starts. The first meeting should happen during orientation, not during the chaos of the first week. Establish meeting times, communication norms, and the scope of the mentoring relationship before it is needed.</p>
<h3>5. The unwritten rules</h3>
<p>Every school has them. The teachers&#39; lounge is where people vent; do not repeat what you hear. The principal prefers email over drop-ins. The custodian controls who gets the good supplies, and being friendly to them is not optional. Mrs. Chen down the hall is the person who knows everything and will help anyone who asks.</p>
<p>Veteran teachers navigate these invisible systems effortlessly. New teachers stumble through them painfully. A 30-minute conversation with a veteran colleague about the unwritten rules of the building saves months of awkward learning.</p>
<h2>The first semester: structured support</h2>
<h3>Weeks 1-2: Daily check-ins</h3>
<p>A mentor, instructional coach, or administrator should check in with every new teacher daily during the first two weeks. Not a formal meeting. A two-minute stop-by: &quot;How was today? What do you need?&quot; This frequency communicates that the new teacher is not alone.</p>
<h3>Weeks 3-6: Weekly structured meetings</h3>
<p>Shift to weekly 30-minute meetings with the mentor. Focus on immediate challenges: a difficult class period, a parent who is upset, a lesson that fell apart. The mentor&#39;s role is to normalize struggle, share strategies, and reassure.</p>
<h3>Months 2-4: Observation and feedback</h3>
<p>New teachers should observe veteran teachers at least twice and receive non-evaluative observation from their mentor at least twice. This reciprocal observation is the highest-leverage professional development for a first-year teacher.</p>
<h3>Months 5-9: Gradual release</h3>
<p>As the new teacher gains confidence, shift from support to professional growth. What instructional strategies do they want to develop? What professional goals do they have? The mentor relationship evolves from crisis management to coaching.</p>
<div class="metrics-box">

<h2>What to measure</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>First-year retention rate</strong> (what percentage of new hires complete year one?)</li>
<li><strong>New teacher satisfaction survey</strong> (quarterly, focused on support quality)</li>
<li><strong>Mentor meeting frequency</strong> (are meetings happening as scheduled?)</li>
<li><strong>Onboarding program completion</strong> (did new teachers complete all orientation components?)</li>
<li><strong>Time to effectiveness</strong> (how quickly do new teachers reach proficiency on classroom observations?)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="mistakes-box">

<h2>Common mistakes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scheduling orientation with no classroom setup time.</strong> New teachers need time in their classroom before students arrive. Protect this time.</li>
<li><strong>Covering only logistics and ignoring culture.</strong> Knowing how the copy machine works is important. Knowing the unwritten rules of the building is more important.</li>
<li><strong>Assigning a mentor and never checking whether they meet.</strong> A mentor assignment is not a mentoring relationship. Verify that meetings are happening.</li>
<li><strong>Treating new teacher support as a first-semester initiative.</strong> The second semester is when burnout hits hardest. Support should extend through the full first year and taper in year two.</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="sources-list">

<h2>Sources</h2>
<ol>
<li>Ingersoll, R. M. (2012). &quot;Beginning Teacher Induction: What the Data Tell Us.&quot; Phi Delta Kappan.</li>
<li>New Teacher Center, &quot;New Teacher Support Framework&quot; (2023).</li>
<li>National Center for Education Statistics, &quot;Teacher Attrition and Mobility&quot; (2024).</li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><strong>If you only do one thing this week:</strong> Ask each of your first-year teachers to list the three things they wish someone had told them before day one. Compile the answers. Add them to next year&#39;s orientation. Each year, this exercise makes your onboarding stronger.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Crystal DiFrancesca</author>
            <category>Teacher Retention</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>